<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the conversion of sinners to God in Christ: The [bracket] 1. necessity, 2. nature, [double bracket] 3. means, 4. signs of it. With a concluding speech to the unconverted. / By Martin Fynch ...</title>
            <author>Finch, Martin, 1628?-1698.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 97 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09141</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 124064177</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F944B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177058</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">124064177</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 124064177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">192261</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09141)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 192261)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2909:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the conversion of sinners to God in Christ: The [bracket] 1. necessity, 2. nature, [double bracket] 3. means, 4. signs of it. With a concluding speech to the unconverted. / By Martin Fynch ...</title>
                  <author>Finch, Martin, 1628?-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 166, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Mortlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Toronto Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Conversion --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:3"/>
            <p>OF THE CONVERSION OF <hi>SINNERS</hi> TO <hi>God in Chriſt: The</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Neceſſity,</item>
                  <item>2. Nature,</item>
                  <item>3. Means,</item>
                  <item>4. Signs of it.</item>
               </list> WITH A concluding SPEECH to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCONVERTED.</hi> By <hi>MARTIN FYNCH</hi> a Servant of Chriſt in the Work of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>Except a man be born again he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God;
<bibl>
                  <hi>John 3.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Repent therefore and be converted, that your ſins may be blotted out, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come from the preſence of the Lord;</q>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Acts 3.19.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <q>Then will I teach tranſgreſſors thy ways, and ſinners ſhall be turned unto thee;
<bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 51.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Mortlock,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Phoenix</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1680.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:5"/>
            <head>TO THE INHABITANTS OF Great <hi>GRIMSBY</hi> IN THE COUNTY of <hi>LINCOLN,</hi> Salvation in Chriſt Jeſus our LORD.</head>
            <p>IT is ſaid of <hi>Paul</hi> when he was at <hi>Athens,</hi> his ſpirit was ſtirred when he ſaw the City wholy given to Idolatry. <hi>Act. 17.17.</hi> The Servants of Christ are to have their Spirits ſtirred with a <hi>Holy Zeal</hi> for God, and with bowels of compaſſion to
<pb facs="tcp:192261:6"/>the Souls of men; when they ſee Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wholy given to ignorance and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs. That is a good ſtirring of our Spirits, and from the <hi>Holy</hi> Spirit of God, to endeavour to turn men from darkneſs unto light, and from the power of <hi>Satan</hi> unto God. Charity to the Souls of Men is the higheſt Charity; thoſe that know the terrour of the Lord, and what a fearful thing it is to fall into the bands of the living God ſhould be very earneſt to perſwade men to flee from the wrath to come, if by any means they may be inſtruments in Chriſts hand to ſave ſome: This ſmall <hi>Treatiſe</hi> written in your <hi>Town,</hi> and much for your ſakes, I dedicate unto you as a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of my love to your ſouls; I write not unto you about controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and about leſſer things, my deſign is higher, that is, to ſhew the neceſſity of the New Birth; and the Nature there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of If Perſons be truly converted from Sin to Chriſt; though they may erre and miſtake in ſomethings about the
<pb facs="tcp:192261:6"/>manner of the outward worſhip of God in this World, God will ſooner or later reveal it unto them, or however Pardon it to them through his grace in Christ, ſo that thoſe miſtakes ſhall not hinder their Salvation. But if perſons be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo right in the outward way of their profeſſion and worſhip, and yet be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to a work of grace and converſion upon their hearts, they cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>There are two ſorts of Perſons eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, with whom I have to do in this <hi>Treatiſe;</hi> Firſt thoſe that think that the practiſe of ſome formalities and outward things will bring them to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven without a work of grace and converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon their Souls. If men think that the being of this or that Church, and being of this or that way of outward profeſſion of Religion, will bring them to everlaſting Life, whilſt in the mean time they are groſſly ignorant of the things of God; of looſe and licentious lives or unacquainted with a Sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing change wrought by the Spirit of God
<pb facs="tcp:192261:7"/>upon their Souls, let them conſider what is written in this Book, to undeceive them, and ſhew them what of neceſſity muſt be done, or elſe they are undone for ever. The ſecond ſort that I deal with in this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> are thoſe who though they are for devotion, ſtrictneſs of Life and a change of mens Spirits and ways, yet carry it no further then a kind of Civility, <hi>Moral</hi> vertues and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life produced by a meer awe of a Deity and fear of <hi>Hell</hi> without the true knowledge of Chriſt and faith in him; In true Converſion there is a coming to Chriſt, a receiving of Chriſt, a being Sanctified by Faith in him. Chriſt is little known as the juſtifier and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier too of lost and ſinful man. Chriſt is made uſe of by many, but as upon the by, and for faſhion-ſake both in the matter of juſtification, and in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of converſion; therefore it is the deſign of this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> to lead men to a more diſtinct knowledg of Chriſt, and that they may ſe how God bleſſeth us with all ſpiritual bleſſings, in heavenly
<pb facs="tcp:192261:7"/>things in him. I have not adorned this diſcourſe after the manner of ſome, I Study to ſet forth the things of God to the meaneſt capacity. I wiſh what I have written were yet more plain and eaſier to be underſtood. Now that the God of all grace would bleſs what I have written to the furtherance of your ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and to the everlaſting good of others, who ſhall peruſe it, is the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant in Chriſt, <hi>MARTIN FYNCH.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:8"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> I. OF the Neceſſity of <hi>Converſion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> II. That in the ordinary way of the Lords converting of Souls, God doth firſt work upon men in a more common way, making a change upon men which yet falls ſhort of ſaving work.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> III. Sheweth, what Special Grace and ſaving Converſion is.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> IV. Sheweth, what outward means God is pleaſed to make uſe of in the Converſion of Souls.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> V. Sheweth, that whatſoever out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means the Lord makes uſe of for the Converſion of Souls, the work is done by his own Almighty Power.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> VI. Sheweth, that God converts men at ſeveral Ages, ſome in youth, ſome in their latter time, as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> VII. Sheweth, how we may know that we are Converted and paſſed from death to Life.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> VIII. Is a concluding Speech to the unconverted.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:192261:8"/>
            <head>THE <hi>NECESSITY</hi> OF <hi>Converſion.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the Neceſſity of Converſion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BEfore I open the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion,</hi> it is requiſite that I ſhould ſpeak ſomething of the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> thereof.</p>
               <p>This Propoſition therefore I lay down; <hi>That every Man by Nature is ſo Degenerated from God, ſo utterly corrupted and tainted by Sin, ſo prone to all Evil, ſo oppoſite to God and all that is ſpiritually good, that except he
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:192261:9"/>be Converted and Changed, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a twofold <hi>Miſery</hi> come upon us by our <hi>Fall</hi> in <hi>Adam:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>The loſs of the Favour of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>The loſs of the Image of God</hi> in <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, We have loſt the <hi>Favour of God</hi> by <hi>Sin,</hi> ſo that as we are by <hi>Nature the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath,</hi> Epheſ. 2.3. <hi>God is angry with us,</hi> Pſal. 7.11. <hi>We are under the Curſe of his holy Law,</hi> Galat. 3.10. The Law cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us for <hi>Original Sin:</hi> the Law curſeth us for <hi>Actual Sins.</hi> The Law pronounceth the <hi>Sinner</hi> to be <hi>vile and abominable to God:</hi> to be ſuch a One as his <hi>Soul hath no pleaſure in,</hi> but will bring into <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> according to all the Evil that he hath done to <hi>provoke the Eyes of his Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now from this part of our <hi>Miſery</hi> we are recovered by the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Justification,</hi> which <hi>is an act of Gods free Grace, whereby he forgives a poor Sinner for Chriſts ſake all Trespaſſes, and imputeth the perfect and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious righteouſneſs of Chriſt as our Mediator and Surety to make him pure, clean, and without ſpot in his ſight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This great <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> is held forth in ſuch Scriptures as theſe: <hi>In the Lord
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:192261:9"/>ſhall all the houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>be juſtified, and ſhall glory,</hi> Iſa. 45.25. <hi>This is the Name where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſhall be called,</hi> (ſpeaking of Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>The Lord our righteouſneſs,</hi> Jer. 23.6. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing juſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption which is in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 3.23. <hi>But to him that worketh not, but belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſneſs.</hi> Even as <hi>David</hi> alſo deſcribeth <hi>the bleſſedneſs of the man unto whom God imputeth righteouſneſs without works,</hi> Rom. 4.5, 6. <hi>But of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus, who is made of God unto us wiſdom and righteouſneſs, and ſanctification and redemption,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.30.</p>
               <p>Moſt excellently doth the holy Scripture ſet ſorth this Point, telling us, <hi>That there is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> that their Sins are blotted out, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred no more, caſt into the depths of the Sea; not imputed unto them, caſt behind Gods back; and that in Chriſt Believers are righteous, all fair, and no ſpot in them. God beholding them cloathed and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the beſt Robe, the Garment of Salvation: he is not aſhamed to be called their God, and their Father, but taketh them near unto him, to ſtand before him for ever.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:192261:10"/>
               <p>The Lords marrying of a Soul to Chriſt, by giving us Faith in him, doth actually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit us from the debt of Sin: Chriſt our heavenly Husband anſwereth all. As we need no more to bring us into an actual ſtate of Condemnation, but that we come to be actually in the <hi>firſt Adam;</hi> ſo we need no more to our <hi>actual Juſtification,</hi> then that we be actually in Chriſt the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> who is a root of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> to all that are in him.</p>
               <p>As there is a <hi>Fountain</hi> and <hi>firſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Adam</hi> and his <hi>Poſterity</hi> in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works: So there is a <hi>Fountain</hi> and <hi>firſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Elect</hi> in the Covenant of Redemption. And as <hi>Wrath</hi> and <hi>Condemnation</hi> ſtand ready to ſeize upon us, as ſoon as we come to be actually in <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe of what he hath done in our own room, as our Head and publick Perſon: So <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Juſtification</hi> ſtand rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be beſtowed upon the <hi>Elect</hi> as ſoon a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they come to be actually in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of what he hath done and ſuffered i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their room and ſtead.</p>
               <p>As we are not actually in <hi>Adam</hi> till w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come to be quickned in the Womb of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> So we are not actually in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we come to be quickned in the Womb o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:192261:10"/>
               <p>As when we come actually to have impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us the <hi>Guilt of</hi> Adams <hi>Sin,</hi> we have an inherent <hi>taint</hi> and <hi>corruption</hi> of our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> from him: So when we come to have the <hi>Righteouſneſs of Chriſt</hi> actually imputed to us, we have <hi>inherent Grace</hi> and <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> of our <hi>Nature</hi> from him. So that as the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> is the Root both of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation</hi> and <hi>Corruption</hi> to us: So the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Adam</hi> is the Root both of <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification</hi> to us.</p>
               <p>When the Scripture ſaith, <hi>We are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Faith,</hi> it is not meant that we are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by it as a <hi>work or quality,</hi> but that by this <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> we receive <hi>Chriſt</hi> who juſtifies us.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> by which we are <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> is a <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> without us: the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> of another, wrought by another, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in another; it is the <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt, God-Man.</hi> That <hi>Robe of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> which covers our Sins, is put on by <hi>Faith,</hi> and we wear it here and for ever in <hi>Heaven:</hi> But though it be upon us (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) <hi>the righteouſneſs of God which is by faith in Jeſus Chriſt, is unto all and upon all them that believe,</hi> Rom. 3.22. Yet it is never <hi>inherent</hi> in us, but only <hi>imputed</hi> to us.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:192261:11"/>
               <p>No man under Heaven hath a perſect <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal righteouſneſs</hi> of his own to <hi>juſtifie him,</hi> therefore he muſt have an <hi>Evangelical righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> that is a <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> that anſwers the <hi>Law,</hi> but is brought to light by the <hi>Gospel.</hi> No man hath a <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of his own to <hi>juſtifie him,</hi> therefore he muſt have the <hi>righteouſneſs of another</hi> even the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Jeſus our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtification</hi> is perfect when we firſt <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt,</hi> though not as to our <hi>partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation</hi> of all the <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>comfort,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed effects</hi> of it; ſo it extends it ſelf to <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> yet 'tis <hi>perfect</hi> in it ſelf, becauſe the <hi>righteouſneſs of Chriſt</hi> which we receive in our <hi>firſt believing,</hi> is a <hi>perfect righteouſneſs:</hi> we never have any other to <hi>juſtifie us</hi> at Gods Bar, neither do we need any other. We rejoyce and glory more and more in the <hi>righteouſneſs of Christ,</hi> are more taken with this <hi>best Robe,</hi> and are more thankful for it: But this <hi>Robe of righteouſneſs</hi> that covers Sins, and makes us lovely in the eyes of the Lord, is <hi>the ſame for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification</hi> muſt by no means be confounded: The <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> is for one purpoſe, the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification</hi> for another. <hi>Juſtification</hi> is for the taking away of the <hi>guilt of ſin; Sanctification</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:192261:11"/>for the taking away of the <hi>filth and power</hi> of it. <hi>Juſtification</hi> brings us into a ſtate of <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> and <hi>acceptation</hi> with God; <hi>Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is to enable us to walk ſuitable to this <hi>New</hi> and <hi>happy Eſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> is not our <hi>Half-Saviour,</hi> and works the <hi>other half,</hi> or any <hi>part of a Saviour;</hi> but <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>All</hi> in this <hi>buſineſs.</hi> There is <hi>a waſhing of Regeneration,</hi> which is alſo from <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Saviour,</hi> Titus, 3.5. But this is of another nature and to other ends and purpoſes then the <hi>waſhing of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> Not only Miniſters, but all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers ſhould labour to have a clear and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct knowledge of the <hi>Doctrine of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> for it is our <hi>Life.</hi> When the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>That</hi> Abraham <hi>was juſtified by works,</hi> the meaning is, <hi>That he was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, declared and manifeſted to be a true Believer by his works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Holy Scriptures ſpeaks of the Lords <hi>giving rewards and eternal life,</hi> upon <hi>working</hi> and <hi>obedience.</hi> Thoſe Scriptures muſt be underſtood <hi>declaratively,</hi> not <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually,</hi> that is as nothing, and declaring who are the perſons to whom he gives eternal life, and <hi>not as ſhewing the cauſe</hi> thereof, for that is only his <hi>free grace in Chriſt.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thoſe Scriptures ſhew the certain <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:192261:12"/>that there is between <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> that where the Lord freely gives <hi>Glory hereafter,</hi> there he gives <hi>Grace here.</hi> What is <hi>Glory in heaven</hi> for the ſubſtance of it, but <hi>Grace, Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> with God <hi>perfected:</hi> So that ſuch Scriptures hold forth no more but this, <hi>That whom the Lord juſtifies freely by his Grace in Christ, and ſanctifieth in him; he trains them up in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, obedience, and fellowſhip with him, until he brings them to the fulneſs of that, which at firſt they have but the laſt and the firſt fruits of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that when afterwards in this Diſcourſe I ſpeak of a <hi>ſaving work of the Spirit</hi> wrought in thoſe whom the Lord bringeth unto life. You muſt not think that this <hi>work of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi> is the matter of our <hi>Juſtification.</hi> By <hi>Grace we are ſaved,</hi> freely by <hi>Grace</hi> through the <hi>Redemption which is in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> The work of <hi>Converſion,</hi> and the <hi>Graces of the Spirit</hi> wrought in us, do only accompany <hi>Salvation,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.9. are wrought in thoſe that are ſaved, and go along with them, and accompany them to Heaven: Yea, thoſe <hi>Graces</hi> for the ſubſtance leave them not, when they have accompanied them thither, but are perſected here. But
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:192261:12"/>the <hi>work of Converſion</hi> is called <hi>a ſaving work of the Spirit,</hi> becauſe it is wrought in all them, and onely in them who are ſaved by the <hi>free grace of God in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now my way will be clearer to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We have, as we are in the ſtate of <hi>Nature</hi> loſt the <hi>Image of God,</hi> conſiſting in <hi>ſpiritual knowledge, holineſs</hi> and <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. Regeneration</hi> is wrought in thoſe that are ſaved, to deliver them from this part of their <hi>Miſery.</hi> Man was at firſt made upright, made in the Image of God, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of thoſe <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>heavenly Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> he was furniſhed with. But it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with us by our <hi>Fall;</hi> our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is darkned like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> our Eyes are put out.</p>
               <p>That glimmering of light to know that there is a God, and that ſome things are evil and ſome things good, ſeems rather to be <hi>a new Gift of God,</hi> and <hi>common Illumination of the Spirit</hi> ſince the <hi>Fall of Adam,</hi> to be ſome curb and reſtraint to Sin in the World, then any remainder of Gods Image, which was upon us in our <hi>firſt Creation.</hi> For the peace of Gods Church, for the benefit of humane Society, and ſuch like reaſons, God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows this <hi>common illumination</hi> and <hi>conviction</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:192261:13"/>upon men, without which this World would be like <hi>Hell,</hi> and men would be like <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Marvel not at this ſaying, <hi>that men would be ſo vile,</hi> if it were not for this <hi>common il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>common light</hi> that God giveth to the Sons of Men; ſeeing the <hi>Nature</hi> of Man is wholly corrupted, and the thoughts of his heart <hi>are evil, and onely evil, and that continually.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A dangerous miſtake it is of the people commonly called <hi>Quakers,</hi> that they make the heeding and attending to this <hi>common light</hi> to be <hi>Converſion,</hi> (which thing is to be found among many ſober Heathens.) But it is not to be much wonder'd at in that <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> ſeeing they are generally very <hi>Ignorant,</hi> even of the very <hi>Fundamentals of Religion.</hi> 'Tis true, this <hi>common light</hi> is a great <hi>Gift of God</hi> to the World, to keep up ſome <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>common honeſty</hi> amongſt men: But the <hi>New Birth</hi> and <hi>true Converſion</hi> is a thing of a far higher Nature, conſiſting in a more ſpecial <hi>Illumination</hi> of the Spirit, to ſhew us our <hi>loſt eſtate by Nature,</hi> and to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal Chriſt</hi> to us as an Object of Faith; and it is ſuch a work of the Spirit upon the Soul, as doth enable us to believe on the <hi>Name of the Son of God,</hi> to mourn for Sin, to hate
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:192261:13"/>Sin, and to walk in Obedience unto God, not meerly from Convictions of Conſcience, and fear of the Wrath to come, but from a delight to do the Will of God, and a fixed Principle of Goſpel ingenuity and gratitude to God, for the exceeding riches of his Grace and kindneſs towards us through Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>But for a further diſcovery of the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedneſs and corruption of our Nature, whereby it may appear that there is ſuch a need of a new Birth and Converſion, let us conſider things more particularly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As was touched before, There is <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful ignorance in men about Heavenly things:</hi> It is an amazing thing if you enquire into people (yea thoſe that are grown to be Men and Women, yea many that have gray hairs upon them) how ignorant they are about <hi>Adams Fall,</hi> Man's loſt eſtate by <hi>Nature,</hi> the <hi>Incarnation of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by him:</hi> And if ſo many be ſo groſly ignorant amongſt us where they have the <hi>Bible</hi> in their own <hi>Tongue,</hi> and where they live under the <hi>Preaching of the Word,</hi> and ſuch helps to get <hi>Knowledge;</hi> how <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant</hi> and <hi>ſpiritually blind</hi> are we by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and without the <hi>means of light!</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There is <hi>a ſtrange careleſneſs in man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:192261:14"/>his future and Eternal State;</hi> looking only at theſe ſeen things which are tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; That except a man be awakened and rouſed up by Afflictions, or Convictions of the Spirit, men are in a profound and deep ſleep, and take no care what ſhall become of their Souls when they die and go hence: But live without ſtudying of the Scriptures, without ſerious and conſtant praying to God, without ſpeaking of Heavenly matters at all, as if they had not immortal Souls that muſt be happy or miſerable for ever in another World And if one tell them of Heaven and Hell, and that upon this moment depends Eternity, they think a man is Brain-ſick and Fantaſtical.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is a proneneſs, yea, <hi>a ſtrong bent and inclination in man to all evil,</hi> To Blaſpheming of God, to Murder, to Theft, to Covetouſneſs, to all kinds of Uncleanneſs, to Drunkenneſs, to Lying; and though by education, company, employment, terrors of Conſcience, fear of puniſhment from God or man, reſpect to name, and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the World, and by the temper and conſtitution of the Body, this wicked bent of the heart may be much curbed and kept in; yet there is in all by nature, ſuch an evil frame and diſpoſition, that there is no
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:192261:14"/>ſin ſo black, ſo horrible, ſo hainous, but man is prone to it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There is in man, not only an <hi>Indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> but <hi>Oppoſition of the heart to any thing that good is,</hi> not onely to Goſpel Grace and Holineſs to believe in Chriſt, to repent, and to walking in the Spirit, but even to Civility and Morality, and thoſe things which yet natural men many times do. So that, I take that common change that is in men, from the groſſeſt vices, to ſome ſobriety, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and juſtice, to proceed not from the power of corrupt nature, but from a kind of common Grace, and common Illumination of the Spirit, which God diſtributeth to man as it pleaſes him, to make him uſeful to humane Society.</p>
               <p>If there be any need to enlarge upon this Subject, to ſhew the Sinfulneſs and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of man by Nature, (omitting many other ways of Sin) let us but ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Sins of the Eye, the Sins of the Tongue, and the Sins of the Thoughts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Sins of the Eye</hi> ſhew the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full corruption that is within the heart of man. Sin within in the heart ſits looking out at thoſe Windows of the eyes,; and there when it ſeeth a ſuitable Object how it luſts after it: When we ſee beauty, then we have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:192261:15"/>wanton eyes, when we ſee fine houſes and riches we have covetous eyes or envious eyes; when we view our own gifts and greatneſs, and converſe with thoſe that are below us, what ſcornful eyes and looks have we? The eye is a curious piece of Gods workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, all the Angels in Heaven could not make ſuch a piece, 'tis the moſt beautifull member of the Body, and it is the light of the Body; it is endowed with a marvellous power to diſcern and take in Objects; the eye ſhould be pure, holy, chaſt: But it is full of Adultery, Covetouſneſs, Pride and Envy. Even Holy <hi>Job,</hi> one in the State of Grace was fain to make a Covenant with his eyes, and put a Law and reſtraint upon them. It is ſtrange what impreſſions are made upon the mind from the ſight ofthe eye in a moment, how the eye affecteth the heart and ſtirreth up the corruptions of it: There may more corruption be ſtirred in the heart by one glance of the eye, than we can get rid of many days, it may be weeks: Even thoſe that are in the ſtate of Grace have need to watch the outward ſenſes of the Body. The eye makes ſuddain and ſtrong impreſſions on the mind. Ah! what need is there to look to Chriſt for a chaſt eye, a mortified eye, a ſanctified eye.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:192261:15"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Sins of the Tongue</hi> ſhew the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Corruption that is within in the heart of man. <hi>The Tongue is a fire, an unruly evil, full of deadly poyſon, James</hi> 3.6, 7, 8. <hi>Full of curſing and bitterneſs, Rom.</hi> 3.14. The Tongue and Speech is an excellent gift of God; 'tis mans glory above a Beaſt, that he can expreſs his mind by Speech, but man maketh it his ſhame.</p>
               <p>If all our paſſionate Speeches, proud and boaſting Speeches, backbiting Speeches, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene and filthy Speeches; lyes, curſes, oaths, indiſcreet, raſh and idle words throughout our whole Lives ſhould be written down, what a ſtrange Book would it be?</p>
               <p>So much Sin is committed by the Tongue and ſuch an unruly evil it is, that <hi>David,</hi> a man in the ſtate of Grace, and one that was eminent in Grace too, prays earneſtly to God <hi>to ſet a watch before his mouth, and to keep the door of his lips.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>The Sins of the Thoughts</hi> do ſhew the wonderfull corruption that is within in the the heart of man: There is nothing that may ſooner convince us of our own vileneſs, and make us cry out, <hi>We are unclean, We are unclean,</hi> than a ſerious reflection upon our Thoughts. O how many proud Thoughts, wanton Thoughts, envious
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:192261:16"/>Thoughts, uncharitable Thoughts, diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Thoughts! What a multitude of ſinful Thoughts ariſe in the heart in a little time, then what a numberleſs number is there in ones whole life that lives any conſiderable time in the World. <hi>None but he that telleth the number of the Stars, and calleth them all by their names, is able to count the number of our vain and ſinful thoughts, and he knoweth all the thoughts that come into our minds every one of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for good and holy Thoughts, if God did not put them in and keep them in the heart, how rarely ſhould we have a thought of God, of Death, of Heaven, and the way that leadeth unto Eternal Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Thoughts of Fooliſhneſs is ſin</hi> though it never come into outward act, there is Heart Adultery, Heart Theft, Heart Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Heart Diſobedience to Parents, Heart Blaſphemy againſt God, Heart Pride. He knoweth nothing almoſt of Religion, that knoweth not that Thoughts may be Sin as well as outward acts, and that abundance of ſin may be committed in the heart that never appeareth in the Life. After Converſion nothing uſually humbles men more than the ſinfulneſs of the Thoughts and the unſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:192261:16"/>of the heart to God; ſinful thoughts were far more before God wrought upon them: but as <hi>Believers</hi> grow more <hi>spiritual</hi> and <hi>holy,</hi> the more they take notice of their <hi>Heart-ſins,</hi> and abhor themſelves for them.</p>
               <p>What ſhould I more ſay, to ſet forth the corruption of our <hi>Nature,</hi> whole Volumes might be written of this <hi>Subject,</hi> and yet the half, no not the thouſand part told us of it. But it is briefly comprehended in thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>Mark</hi> 7.21, 22. <hi>For from within out of the heart of men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed evil thoughts, adultery, fornication, murders, thefts, covetouſneſs, wickedneſs, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, an evil eye, blasphemy, pride, fooliſhneſs.</hi> And in <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 17.9. <hi>The heart is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful above all things, and deſperately wicked, who can know it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To treat fully therefore of the corruption of <hi>Man's Nature,</hi> is one of the vaſteſt <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> that can be ſpoken of, next to that of the <hi>Immenſity</hi> and <hi>Infiniteneſs</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Grace</hi> in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but theſe few things are written of it, that we might know the Plague of our own hearts, as an Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the following Diſcourſe, that we may ſee what need we have to believe on the <hi>Name of the Son of God,</hi> that we may be pardoned and ſanctified through him.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:192261:17"/>
               <p>By what hath been already ſaid, we may ſee what a groſs and dangerous miſtake it is of thoſe that think there is no other <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> than being <hi>Baptized,</hi> and taking upon us the outward profeſſion of <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> Now that any ſhould ſpeak thus, and count all trouble of Conſcience about our <hi>eternal eſtate,</hi> and looking after a work of <hi>Grace upon our Souls,</hi> to be Enthuſiaſm, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly and Mopiſhneſs, ſhews their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful ignorance of the Scriptures, and their utter unacquaintedneſs with the <hi>Grace of God</hi> in their own <hi>Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the holy Scripture ſpeaks ſo much of a <hi>new heart and spirit; of the taking away of the heart of ſtone, and giving us an heart of fleſh: of writing Gods Laws in the heart: of putting his fear into our hearts: of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing our hearts:</hi> and ſpeaks of the <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of being born again: of believing on Chriſt: of repentance and holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> To make all this to be onely our being baptized, and making an outward profeſſion of <hi>Religion,</hi> ſhews men to be wholly ſtrangers to the way that leadeth to <hi>eternal life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſuch men as they are utterly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the caſe and condition of <hi>Souls,</hi> that are in ſpiritual trouble and fear of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:192261:17"/>wrath to come, crying out, <hi>What ſhall we do to be ſaved?</hi> So they preſcribe as ſtrange remedies for their cure; as to be merry, to go into Company, to play at Cards, to go to Plays, and ſuch like: when if they get rid of their trouble for ſin by ſuch means, and be not brought to Chriſt, who onely can give them reſt; their remedy is worſe than their diſeaſe, and they had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter continue in their trouble of Spirit, than find eaſe by ſuch things.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:192261:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>COMMON WORKINGS</hi> of the <hi>SPIRIT.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP II. <hi>That in the ordinary way of the Lord's Converting of Souls, God doth firſt work upon men in a more common way, making a change upon, men which yet fall ſhort of a Saving Work.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat there is a <hi>Common work of the Spirit</hi> upon men, as well as a <hi>Special</hi> and <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving work,</hi> appears by many Scriptures: Thoſe Hearers and Profeſſors that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the <hi>Stony ground, and heard the word with joy,</hi> Matth. 13. have common motions and workings of the Spirit; and ſo have ſuch as are called <hi>the fooliſh Virgins, that took their Lamps and went forth to meet
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:192261:18"/>the Bridegroom.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſhews, that ſome eſcape the <hi>pollutions of the world</hi> (in a ſenſe) and yet return with the <hi>Dog to his vomit;</hi> are again intangled and quite overcome by their old ſins, and their latter end is worſe than their beginning. So likewiſe we read of thoſe that have been enlightned and taſted of the <hi>Heavenly gift,</hi> and of the <hi>Powers of the world to come,</hi> and yet fall away.</p>
               <p>Not that theſe Scriptures or any other, do hold forth a total and final Apoſtacy in any from <hi>ſpecial grace,</hi> but onely from <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon grace.</hi> The Doctrine of the certainty of the perſeverance of all ſound <hi>Believers,</hi> ſhines forth ſo gloriouſly from many plain Texts of Scripture, and from the Nature of the Covenant of Grace, and the purchaſe that Chriſt hath made for them that are his; and the Almightineſs of God, who hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken and promiſed to keep them, that they ſhall not depart from him and periſh: that there is ſcarce any part of Religion that hath been controverted, that is with more facility defended againſt all Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers.</p>
               <p>But ſuch Scriptures hold forth that there is <hi>Common Grace,</hi> as well as <hi>Special: Judas</hi> his <hi>profeſſion</hi> and <hi>gifts: Simon Magus</hi> his <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:192261:19"/>when he ſaw the Miracles and Signs which were done: <hi>Herod</hi>'s hearing <hi>John Baptist</hi> gladly, and doing many things: <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s being almoſt perſwaded to be a <hi>Chriſtian:</hi> come all under this Head of <hi>Common workings of the Spirit;</hi> ſo called, becauſe that not onely thoſe that are <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> but thoſe that <hi>periſh,</hi> have many times ſuch <hi>workings of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now therefore obſerve, that amongſt thoſe that God is pleaſed to beſtow <hi>Common grace</hi> upon, ſome are ordained to <hi>eternal life;</hi> and upon theſe the Lord ſooner or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beſtows <hi>ſpecial grace.</hi> And as for others, the holy Lord doth either by the common motions and influences of his Spirit, keep them in the profeſſion and practice of it all their days; in his infinite wiſdom and good pleaſure making uſe of their common grace and gifts for the good of others, and for the preventing of their own greater damnation; or elſe God in his righteous judgment ſo ordereth it, that thoſe common influences and workings of the Spirit depart from them, and ſo they openly fall away into groſs errour or profaneneſs of life to their greater damnation.</p>
               <p>As to <hi>Common Grace</hi> and preparatory <hi>workings of the Spirit,</hi> ſome carry that point
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:192261:19"/>ſo far that they confound <hi>common</hi> and <hi>spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Grace,</hi> darken the Doctrine of <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and caſt a ſtumbling block before weak Chriſtians, puzling them exceedingly, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome things under that Head, that are wrought onely in thoſe that are effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually called.</p>
               <p>But theſe things following may be brought under this Head of <hi>Common Grace,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory <hi>workings of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. An <hi>Illumination of the Spirit,</hi> to make impreſſion upon the Soul, that there is a God, that Man is fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Mediatour,</hi> that there is <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell;</hi> yea one that hath onely this <hi>common illumination,</hi> may have <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> notional knowledge and utterance about theſe and other points of <hi>Religion,</hi> beyond many ſincere Chriſtians. Hence it is that men may go to Hell with their heads full of knowledge and notions of <hi>Religion:</hi> Some that we think for their knowledge and excellent parts, are happy men, yet may have onely <hi>common illumination</hi> and <hi>periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Conviction of Sin</hi> comes in alſo under this Head of <hi>Common Grace,</hi> and prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory <hi>workings of the Spirit.</hi> The Lord uſeth before he infuſeth <hi>Faith in Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>habit of special grace into the heart,</hi> firſt to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:192261:20"/>convince men of <hi>Sin.</hi> Thoſe that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, in the Second Chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> were firſt <hi>pricked in their hearts</hi> with the ſenſe of their <hi>ſins, verſe</hi> 37. afterwards God gave them <hi>Faith in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What <hi>ſins</hi> the Lord will ſet home upon the Conſcience, firſt of all to awaken and ſtartle a <hi>ſecure Sinner,</hi> depends upon his <hi>holy pleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes the Lord ſhews men ſo much of their own <hi>vileneſs,</hi> as doth almoſt ſink them in their Spirits; ſometimes the Lord dealeth with them in a gentler way: Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally God ſets home <hi>groſs ſins, special ſins,</hi> with moſt terrour upon the heart. It is no matter how long it is ſince the <hi>ſin</hi> hath been committed; God can ſet it home upon the Conſcience with as much terrour, as if it had been but yeſterday.</p>
               <p>The univerſal depravedneſs and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Nature is ſometimes ſet home upon the Conſcience, that the <hi>convinced ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> ſeeth himſelf more vile upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, than upon the account of his <hi>ſinful acts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſaid of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt, that he ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince men of ſin, becauſe they believe not on Chriſt,</hi> John 16.8, 9. From whence we muſt not conclude, that men are not ſo throughly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:192261:20"/>convinced of <hi>ſin,</hi> as God doth convince men in the <hi>preparatory workings of the Spirit,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Lord do ſet it home particularly upon the Conſcience; that the perſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many other <hi>ſins,</hi> is guilty of the <hi>ſin</hi> of <hi>unbelief,</hi> taking it for the Soul's not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Chriſt, and believing and relying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him as a <hi>Saviour:</hi> But we may take the <hi>not believing on Chriſt</hi> there in a large ſenſe, for being in a courſe of <hi>impenitency</hi> and <hi>graceleſneſs:</hi> Or we may thus conceive the meaning of the place, that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in <hi>converting Souls</hi> will <hi>convince them of ſin,</hi> (what <hi>ſins he pleaſeth</hi>) and ſhew them that they are in danger of <hi>Hell and damnation,</hi> being ſuch perſons as are not yet in <hi>Christ,</hi> and believe not on his <hi>Name,</hi> and ſo have not their <hi>pardon in Chriſt,</hi> to plead for their <hi>diſcharge</hi> from the <hi>guilt of their ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, where perſons have been long under <hi>convictions</hi> of <hi>other ſins,</hi> and have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved under much <hi>preaching of Chriſt,</hi> and yet have gone on a great while in a way of <hi>ſeck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> to be <hi>justified</hi> by their <hi>own righteouſneſs,</hi> and are not brought to give God the <hi>whole glory</hi> of his <hi>free grace in Chriſt,</hi> in <hi>juſtifying</hi> and <hi>ſaving</hi> of them, the Lord may ſet home this <hi>unbelief</hi> of theirs, and ſlighting of <hi>Chriſt</hi> their <hi>onely remedy,</hi> as a great <hi>ſin</hi> and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:192261:21"/>
                  <hi>folly,</hi> but that the Lord doth ſet home this <hi>particularly</hi> upon every one that is under <hi>conviction,</hi> in order to a <hi>ſound converſion,</hi> and that conviction is not <hi>through</hi> and <hi>ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> without this, cannot be made out by Scripture.</p>
               <p>Under this Head it muſt be conſidered, That though the Lord uſeth to <hi>convince men of ſin,</hi> and fright men with the terrours of <hi>the Law,</hi> whom he intends to <hi>convert</hi> and bring to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Yet firſt, all that are <hi>converted</hi> feel not the like <hi>terrours</hi> and <hi>fears</hi> of the <hi>wrath to come,</hi> before their <hi>cloſing with Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Though the ſetting home of <hi>ſin upon the Conſcience,</hi> and putting the <hi>Soul in fear of the wrath to come,</hi> is the <hi>work of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> making uſe of the <hi>terrours of the Law</hi> to that purpoſe; yet not every thing that ſometimes follows the reupon, as a mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding <hi>that he ſhall never find mercy;</hi> or his going on in a <hi>legal way</hi> to <hi>ſeek peace,</hi> and <hi>healing of his wounds by his own righteouſneſs and duties,</hi> without the <hi>blood of Chriſt;</hi> theſe things come not from the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> that firſt convinced the Soul <hi>of ſin,</hi> but from <hi>Satan,</hi> and from the corruption of our own hearts, that mix themſelves, and put in with theſe <hi>convictions</hi> and <hi>workings</hi> of the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:192261:21"/>
               <p n="3">3. All that are <hi>convinced of ſin,</hi> and have <hi>terrours,</hi> yea it may be very great <hi>terrours of Conſcience</hi> thereupon, are not <hi>converted. Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> had great <hi>terrours of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and yet never were <hi>converted:</hi> yet alas, many in giving account of their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion,</hi> build too much upon this, that at ſuch a time they were much troubled for their <hi>ſins,</hi> when as trouble for <hi>ſin</hi> is not a ſufficient evidence of a <hi>ſound converſion,</hi> if it be onely for fear of <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>damnation:</hi> But if after ſight of our <hi>ſins,</hi> and fear of the <hi>wrath of God,</hi> we were brought to know <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to prize <hi>Chriſt</hi> above all, to reſt our weary ſouls upon him, yea upon him alone, and were made <hi>willing in the day of his power,</hi> to take his <hi>yoak</hi> upon us, that as we live by him, we might alſo live to him: then the <hi>work,</hi> the <hi>good work of special and ſaving grace</hi> is begun in us, <hi>Praiſes to Jehovah for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>There is ſome ſtop put to ſin eſpecially groſſe ſin, by this common illumination and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon convictions of the Spirit.</hi> So that a Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing awed with the terrors of the law, dare not run into that exceſſe of riot and prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe that he hath done, but having ſome fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the bitterneſs of ſin cannot commit it with that greedineſs that he hath done.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:192261:22"/>But begins to leave more open and groſs ſins, and perſorm duties of Religion and ſets upon reforming of his Life; and finds ſome kinde of joy and peace therein, which yet we may not think comes from the <hi>comforter</hi> the Holy Ghoſt, for he giveth no joy and peace to any, but what flows from the beholding God's reconciled face in Chriſt, or a reflex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion upon the effects of his grace and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with us, leading us forth in wayes of holineſs and obedience in his Name. So that wee muſt diligently conſider that although theſe common workings of the Spirit, do lay ſome reſtraint upon Sin, and put us upon good duties and reformation of Life, yet wee muſt not reſt here and ſay ſurely the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Death is paſt; but careful muſt we be as for our Lives, that now our Souls be rightly bottomed upon Chriſt, that he may be our righteouſneſs, to juſtify us and the onely Fountaine of ſanctification and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to us.</p>
               <p>Many other things might be added under this head of common grace and preparatory workings of the ſpirit; as that the Lord doth ſometimes make great impreſſions upon men of the holineſs of the Law, of his juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice if he ſhould caſt us into hell, of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of our owne righteouſneſs to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:192261:22"/>make our peace with him and that we muſt come to Chriſt if we would have life.</p>
               <p>But we muſt not extend the preparatory workings of the Spirit to far as ſome do, as if there were any ſaving work upon the ſoul, before union with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>That which I aime at here, is to ſhew that in converſion ordinarily there is legal repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance before Evange lical, ſight and ſenſe of ſin, before Chriſt be brought into the Soul, but no ſpeciall grace and ſaving work untill union with Chriſt and infuſion of a new heart and ſpirit: of theſe things this is the ſum, The Lord doth uſually work common grace, before he works ſpeciall grace: Some have theſe common workings of the Spirit and yet are never ſavingly converted. In the elect theſe common workings of the Spirit are the preparing the way to ſpeciall grace, that the Lord intends to beſtow upon them, that is, that the common illumination, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions and humbling for ſin, that the holy Ghoſt worketh in the elect before their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, are in order to their converſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:192261:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Shewing what Special Grace and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Converſion is.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw to ſhew what Special Grace and Saving Converſion is; Firſt I ſhall give a ſhort definition of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>'Tis a work of the Spirit of God upon the ſoul, whereby the habit, the principle and ſeed of all grace is infuſed, changing and ſanctifying the heart, to the bringing of us to truſt wholly in Chriſt for ſalvation, to repent of our Sins, to love God and unfeignedly deſire to walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in obedience and newneſs of Life ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe who have this change wrought in them are paſſed from death to life, ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly be ſaved and inherit everlaſting Life.</p>
               <p>But to open the doctrine of converſion more fully and plainly to every ones capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I know no better and ſurer way then to explain ſome of thoſe expreſſions of the holy Scripture, by which ſpecial grace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion is ſet forth to us.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:192261:23"/>
               <p>Firſt, ſpecial grace and converſion is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, (eſpecially in the new Teſtament) called believing on Chriſt. To as many as received him, to them he gave power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Sons of God, even to as many as believed on his name. <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <hi>He that believeth on the Son hath everlaſting Life,</hi> John. 3.36. <hi>This is the word of God that ye believe on him whom he hath ſent,</hi> John. 6.29. <hi>Believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved Act.</hi> 16.31. <hi>With the heart Man believeth unto righteouſneſs, Rom.</hi> 10.10. <hi>By grace are ye ſaved through Faith.</hi> Epheſ. 2.8. yea this grace of believing is ſpoken of in the Old Teſtament, though not ſo clearly as in the new.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Look to me and be ſaved,</hi> Iſa 45.22. where by looking is meant believing and <hi>verſ.</hi> 24. <hi>ſurely ſhall one ſay in the Lord</hi> (viz the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> the Mediator) have I righteouſneſs and ſtrength, even to him ſhall men come, 24 <hi>verſ.</hi> where by coming is meant believing. Thoſe that were ſaved under the Old Teſtament ſaw Chriſt's day of coming in the fleſh affar off, and were glad and put their truſt in him, having the ſame ſpirit of Faith in Chriſt, that the Saints have now.</p>
               <p>Well then it is clear that where there is a true believing on Chriſt there is true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:192261:24"/>Now therefore let us inquire when a man doth believe to the ſaving of his ſoul? And there is a neceſſity to enquire into the true nature of Saving Faith; becauſe a Man may have ſome kind of Faith, and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go to Heaven? ſome are ſaid for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while to believe, and afterwards to fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away <hi>Luke.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> is ſaid to believe, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.13. Which Scripture do ſhew that there is an aſſent to the Doctrine of the Goſpel, which is but a temporary Faith, an hiſtorical Faith from common illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and convictions. Yea it is ſaid, the Devils believe and tremble, <hi>James.</hi> 2.3. The devils, by the power of light, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions are forced to believe that there is a God, though yet they are Enemies to him, and wiſh there were no God. The truth is, if a man do believe the Doctrine of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſo as that he maketh no queſtion of the truth thereof, he doth well, and he ought to be thankful for this <hi>common light</hi> and <hi>help of the spirit,</hi> for all men have not this Faith of Aſſent to the truth of Chriſtian Religion. Yea at ſome ſpecial ſeaſons of temptation, a Child of God may be much troubled about ſome main points of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: but the God of all Grace will (after they have ſeen their own weakneſs a while,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:192261:24"/>and been greatly humbled) eſtabliſhed them and ſettle them again. But I ſay, that a meer Aſſent to the truth of Religion, is not enough to prove a man to be converted, for that may be without the true love and liking of Religion in the heart.</p>
               <p>That believing in Chriſt which is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to thoſe that are ſaved, may be thus deſcribed: <hi>It is a principle infuſed by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God into the heart, whereby a poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner inlightned to ſee the truth of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and convinced of his loſt and miſerable eſtate by ſin, and taken off from all hope and confidence in himſelf, doth truſt and rely upon Jeſus Chriſt, our great high Prieſt and Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, to be pardoned and accepted, and be made an Heir of Eternal life through him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The nature of this Grace may be further underſtood, by conſidering how it is ſet forth by various expreſſions in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis called <hi>a truſting in Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>a hoping in Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 1.12, 13. <hi>That we ſhould be to the praiſe of his glory, who firſt truſted in Chriſt,: In whom ye alſo truſted, after that ye heard the word of truth.</hi> Now this Expreſſion holds forth thus much to us, That when a poor Sinner is convinced of his miſerable eſtate by ſin, if the Lord have a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:192261:25"/>gracious purpoſe to him, he will take him off from truſting in any thing in himſelf, to juſtifie him in Gods ſight, and reveal the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to him, the onely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, and <hi>mighty to ſave,</hi> and ſo enable the poor Sinner to truſt in him, and lay the whole weight and ſtreſs of his Soul upon him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Believing in Chriſt, is called <hi>a flieing for refuge, to lay hold upon the hope that is ſet before us in the Gospel,</hi> Heb. 6.18. When the Soul is ſaid to <hi>flee for refuge,</hi> it is an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to the <hi>City of refuge</hi> under the Law, to which the Man-ſlayer was to flee from the <hi>Avenger of blood,</hi> and it is to ſhew, that when the Lord converts a Sinner, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him ſee the danger he is in, he maketh him cry out, <hi>O the Avenger of blood; O the wrath of God is fit to overtake me! How ſhall I eſcape? What ſhall I do?</hi> The Lord fills a poor Sinner with fear and ſolicitouſneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his condition, as the Man-ſlayer under the Law was, about the ſaving of his life from the <hi>Avenger of blood.</hi> If the Lord take delight in us to make us his people, he will convince us of ſin, and make us ſee that the Curſe of the Law is purſuing of us to take vengeance on us for our ſins, and make us cry out for a <hi>City of refuge,</hi> and will ſhew
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:192261:25"/>us that all other things are but <hi>refuges of lies,</hi> and that the Lord Jeſus is the <hi>onely City of refuge,</hi> and ſafety for a poor Sinner to flee unto, he is the <hi>ſtrong City,</hi> the <hi>ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> that is in him will be as Walls and Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks about a poor guilty Sinner for ever, that gets into him: Till Sinners be ſenſible of ſin, and ſee in what an evil caſe and condition they are, the vengeance of <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal fire</hi> being ready to ſeize upon them, they regard not a <hi>City of refuge:</hi> what care they for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> let others look after him and take him that ſee their need of him, they apprehend no danger in their preſent condition; they ſee no need of an <hi>Ark</hi> for the <hi>ſaving of their Souls;</hi> they ſee no <hi>deluge of wrath</hi> coming, till it may be 'tis too late, and then they cry out <hi>an Ark, an Ark, a Chriſt, a Chriſt,</hi> when their <hi>day of Grace</hi> is paſt: They ſee no need of a <hi>City of refuge,</hi> they think they are ſafe and well enough, what ſhould they ſear? till it may be the time is paſt, and the <hi>Gate of the City of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge</hi> ſhut againſt them: then, <hi>O who ſhall bring us into the ſtrong City? Who will bring us into the City of refuge? O a Chriſt, a Chriſt to ſave me, or elſe I am now, even now, ſinking into the bottomleſs Pit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as many as are <hi>ordained to eternal life,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:192261:26"/>ſhall believe on the Name of the Son of God,</hi> to them he ſhall be <hi>precious,</hi> they ſhall make him their <hi>ſtrong City,</hi> their <hi>hiding place,</hi> their <hi>Tower of defence,</hi> and <hi>City of refuge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is another Expreſſion in this place to ſet forth the <hi>work of believing,</hi> and the <hi>Nature</hi> of it, when the Apoſtle ſhews that the deſign of the Soul, in its coming to Chriſt, is to lay hold upon the <hi>hope that is ſet before us in him,</hi> namely, <hi>the hope of pardon, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> and <hi>eternal life.</hi> The Lord ſhews a poor Sinner, that as much as he hath broker the Law, yet there is One that came to <hi>ſeek and to ſave loſt ſinners,</hi> and that there is <hi>hope</hi> ſet before <hi>miſerable ſinners</hi> in the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> and ſo Chriſt is called <hi>our hope,</hi> 1 Tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1.1. the <hi>Object</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> of <hi>Hope,</hi> He it whom there is <hi>hope</hi> for <hi>poor ſinners.</hi> Now then the laying hold of this <hi>hope</hi> is <hi>believing</hi> on Chriſt: Many never knew what it was to <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>tremble,</hi> and ſee what a <hi>ſtorm</hi> their <hi>ſins</hi> had raiſed, that they were in danger to be <hi>caſt away for ever;</hi> nor ever yet knew what it was to Iay hold on the <hi>hope</hi> that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> through Chriſt, to be as the Anchor fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their Souls, both ſure and ſtedfaſt, to hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them and keep them from <hi>eternal ſhip wracks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the way, if any ſhall ſay in theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:192261:26"/>about <hi>believing,</hi> here is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Souls ſubmitting to Chriſts Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, conſenting to be ruled and governed by him renouncing the dominion of <hi>ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, that Frame of ſpirit, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple is wrought in all that do <hi>truly believe;</hi> but there is ſo much ſpoken in the Scripture of <hi>Faith</hi> under theſe notions of <hi>truſting on Coriſt fleeing for refuge to him,</hi> and <hi>laying hold on the hope that is ſet before us in him,</hi> for ſuch reaſons as theſe following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe although when a Soul is <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted,</hi> he takes Chriſt as a <hi>Sanctifier</hi> as well as a Saviour, and is affected with the <hi>filth of ſin,,</hi> as well as the <hi>guilt of ſin;</hi> yet the <hi>principal thing that the Soul is affected withall,</hi> the firſt is, <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> As the Jaylor cried out, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.13. This is not yet ſo fully his great queſtion, <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſanctified?</hi> But O how ſhall I be <hi>ſaved from Hell and eternal damnation,</hi> that I may not have the <hi>wrath of God abide upon me for ever;</hi> and ſo the <hi>poor ſinner</hi> is directed to ſpy out that in Chriſt that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to this great difficulty to ſave it from <hi>wrath,</hi> and in the <hi>receiving</hi> and <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Chriſt</hi> as a <hi>Saviour</hi> and <hi>propitiation</hi> for our <hi>ſins:</hi> the Soul is alſo ſecretly and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully wrought upon, to deſire heartily to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:192261:27"/>be turned from <hi>ſin,</hi> and to <hi>live to Chriſt for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe although where true Faith is, there is a principle of new Obedience alſo, yet <hi>Faith as 'tis ſaid to juſtify, doth onely apprehend and receive Christ, as our perfect righteouſneſs</hi> and attonement with God, and is to be carefully diſtinguiſhed from new Obedience, which in that reſpect is but the effect and concomitant thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe <hi>this is a great, a very great work of the Spirit,</hi> (greater then moſt think) <hi>to bring a poor convinced ſinner to venture his ſoul, and eternall condition upon the Mediation and righteouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Not but they that know him may well put their truſt in him, who is able to ſave to the uttermoſt, all that come to God by him; but for a poor Sinner that ſeeth what a holy, and righteous Law he hath broken, what a great and holy God he hath offended, what great and ſore puniſhment he hath deſerved; and which is infflicted upon the generality of his fellow ſinners to all eternity, when theſe things are realized to a Man, (as they are to thoſe that are brought to Chriſt) and that he is alſo convinced that he hath no righteouſneſs of his own, to make ſatisfaction to the juſtice of God: and to give unto God a ranſom that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:192261:27"/>he ſhould be delivered from going down to the pit. For this Man thus enlightned, awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened and convinced to put his truſt in the righteouſneſs of another, one whom he never ſaw, when he manifeſted himſelf in the fleſh, and ſuffred for ſin, the juſt for the unjuſt; for a poor ſinner to reject all other confidences pitched on by the Sons of men, and to flee onely to this City of refuge, and his heart to truſt faſely there, is an eminent work of the Spirit: And ſo it will appeare when God ſhall be glorified in his Saints, and be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in all them that do believe, not onely for giving ſuch a ſure object of Faith, as <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt is, but for drawing poor ſinners to him. 'Tis an any eaſy thing for ignorant un-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced ſinners, to ſay they have Faith: and ſay they believe on Chriſt; but no Man can come to Chriſt and truly believe on his Name, except he heare and learn of the Father, and be drawn by an Almighty Power unto him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Believing in Chriſt is called in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. <hi>Our coming to Chriſt:</hi> But I ſaid unto you, <hi>that ye alſo have ſeen me, and believe not all that the Father giveth me ſhall come to me,</hi> Joh. 6.36, 37. <hi>If any man thirſt let him come unto mee, and drink.</hi> Joh. 3.7. <hi>Ye will not come unto me, that ye may have life, Joh.</hi> 5.40. By
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:192261:28"/>this coming is not meant a local coming, but a ſpiritual unto Chriſt. He that truly cometh to Chriſt doth, come indeed from the power and filth of Sin, to put himſelf under the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and obedience of the Lord Jeſus: but that which is principally held forth by this coming unto Chriſt, is the coming unto him as a Saviour from the guilt of ſin, to be waſhed and made white in his blood, and be pardoned and juſtified through him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. B lieving in Chriſt is called in the Scripture, <hi>our receiving of Chriſt, to as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the Sons of God, even to as many as believed on his Name,</hi> John. 1.12. Now although every one that truely believeth, receiveth Chriſt in all his Offices, as a <hi>King to rule him,</hi> as <hi>a Prieſt to ſave him,</hi> and as a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to teach him:</hi> yet when <hi>believing</hi> is ſet out by receiving Chriſt, it is meant eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of our <hi>receiving</hi> and <hi>embracing</hi> him as a Saviour, who is in a peculiar manner <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into,</hi> and <hi>dwells in our hearts by faith,</hi> Epheſ 3.17. If any deſire that I ſhould ſpeak a little more to open the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>ſaving Faith,</hi> and ſo to diſtinguiſh it from a common, notional and hiſtorical Faith, it may be done by ſhewing <hi>the special proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> thereof.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:192261:28"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>'Tis a knowing Faith,</hi> 'tis accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ſo much <hi>light</hi> and <hi>knowledge,</hi> as is neceſſary to let Chriſt into the Soul, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that a man is not juſtified by the <hi>works of the Law,</hi> but by the <hi>Faith of Jeſus Chriſt: We have believed on him, that we might be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by the Faith of him,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.16. So that except there be ſome knowledge of the <hi>greatneſs</hi> and <hi>holineſs</hi> of God <hi>with whom we have to do;</hi> ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our <hi>Fall in</hi> Adam, ſome knowledge of <hi>Chriſt the Mediatour,</hi> our eſtate cannot be good; for <hi>how ſhall we believe on him, of whom we have no knowledge?</hi> I ſpeak not here of degrees of <hi>knowledge,</hi> as if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that truly believeth in Chriſt, had a great meaſure thereof, but that there muſt be ſome competent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p>This doth diſtinguiſh <hi>true Faith</hi> from that <hi>ignorant Faith</hi> that many have, who while they think they <hi>believe on Chriſt,</hi> know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their <hi>loſt eſtate</hi> by Nature, and of the <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Mediation</hi> of the <hi>Son of God:</hi> for if men do not know Chriſt in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, neither do they <hi>believe on him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here let me be underſtood, not to ſpeak of <hi>Infants,</hi> nor of <hi>Ideots,</hi> or <hi>deaf and dumb perſons</hi> born ſo, whoſe Ignorance is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:192261:29"/>as to any outward means to bring them to the knowledge of Chriſt, through their <hi>natural incapacity</hi> of receiving <hi>infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> by the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and <hi>Miniſtery</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> we are not to have ſuch hard thoughts of their <hi>condition,</hi> as if none ſuch could be ſaved, for doubtleſs ſome of them are <hi>ſaved,</hi> and even by the <hi>blood of Chriſt,</hi> as well as others, and have the <hi>ſeed</hi> and <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> and the <hi>habit of spiritual knowledge</hi> infuſed into them alſo by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> though in a way altogether undiſcernable to us. And what ſhould hinder, or why ſhould it be thought incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, that <hi>God who quickneth all things,</hi> and infuſes a <hi>rational ſoul</hi> into <hi>Infants</hi> in the <hi>Womb,</hi> and hath given a <hi>rational ſoul</hi> to <hi>Idcots,</hi> (however the actings of it are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by ſome defects of the <hi>Organs</hi> of the <hi>Body:</hi>) I ſay what ſhould hinder but that God can and doth, when it pleaſeth him, infuſe <hi>ſpiritual life,</hi> and the <hi>habit of all grace</hi> into <hi>Infants</hi> and <hi>Ideots.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But for perſons that are growne up to years, and have the exerciſe of reaſon, it is the way of God, if he pleaſe to convert them, ſo to enlighten them as to exerciſe their thoughts about the matters of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to give them a ſight of their Sins
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:192261:29"/>and make known ſenſibly unto them, that Jeſus Chriſt is the only way of help and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for them; So that though there may be knowledge without Faith, yet in grown perſons and thoſe that have the exerciſe of reaſon there cannot be Faith, without ſome competent meaſure of knowledge. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch as are groſly ignorant, and ſcarce know from any inward illumination, whether there be a Chriſt or no, or whether they have any need of him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them from the wrath to come, are not to flatter and deceive themſelves in thinking they believe in Chriſt, becauſe it is not the way of God to make a New Creation in perſons grown up to years, and having the exerciſe of reaſon, but he ſaith <hi>Let there be light.</hi> Commanding Light to ſhine out of darkneſs, and ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into them to give them the knowledge of Jeſus our Lord. I know there is great difference of mens parts, education and the means of knowledge that men have, but God hath none of his Children borne blind altogether, ſpiritually blind, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant. Though men go blindfold to Hell; yet they do not go blindfold to Heaven, but the Lord ſhews them firſt how they are out of the way that leadeth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:192261:30"/>unto Life, and are in the broad way that leadeth to deſtruction and then revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Chriſt to them, as the way to Life, and that Faith in him, repentance and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs do accompany Salvation. Therefore thoſe that are groſly ignorant are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly in a bad eſtate, though they are loath to ſee it, let them conſider what the Scriptures ſay of them. This is a People of no underſtanding, therefore he that made them will not have mercy on them, and he that formed them will ſhew them no favour, <hi>Jſaiah.</hi> 27.11. <hi>They do alwayes erre in their hearts they have not known my wayes,</hi> Heb. 3.10. Which ſhews that Men muſt needs erre in their hearts, and can never walk with God, when they do not know his wayes at all. <hi>There is none that underſtandeth there is none that ſeeketh after God,</hi> Rom. 3.11. Until men come to have ſome underſtanding that they have loſt the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God and his Image, and that there is a way in Chriſt to come unto God and be accepted with him, they will never ſeek after God, if haply they may find him, and ſo we ſee by Luke, 1.70. That thoſe that ſit in darkneſs and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ignorance and blindneſs, they alſo
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:192261:30"/>ſit in the <hi>region and ſhadow of death;</hi> In the very <hi>Suburbs and gate of Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>'Tis a penitent Faith,</hi> that is, true Faith is alwayes accompanied with true repentance; this diſtinguiſheth it from that notional Faith that many have; they pretend to believe in Chriſt, but they never <hi>mourn for ſin,</hi> they do not <hi>loath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for their iniquities.</hi> Some may talk of <hi>Free Grace,</hi> and of <hi>believing in Chriſt,</hi> but look upon <hi>ſorrow for ſin</hi> as a <hi>bondage-frame,</hi> and know not what it is to be <hi>vile in their own eyes,</hi> and <hi>abhor themſelves</hi> for their <hi>evil ways and doings againſt the Lord:</hi> Where it is ſo there, is not <hi>true faith,</hi> their <hi>faith</hi> is but a <hi>fancy</hi> and a <hi>meer notion,</hi> who make <hi>ſin</hi> a light matter, and have their <hi>hearts</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>rent</hi> and <hi>broken</hi> for it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>'Tis an affectionate Faith,</hi> that is, <hi>true Faith</hi> is accompanied with <hi>Love</hi> to the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt,</hi> in whom we do <hi>believe:</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that which <hi>firſt affecteth a poor convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſinner towards Chriſt,</hi> is, <hi>that he is a Saviour and Deliverer from the guilt of ſin:</hi> but in the looking towards him as a <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> the Soul falleth in love with him alſo, as he is <hi>God bleſſed for ever,</hi> and as he is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the <hi>spirit of Grace</hi> in our <hi>Nature;</hi> ſo that <hi>union with him</hi> is every way <hi>deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:192261:31"/>to the Soul:</hi> to them that do believe <hi>Christ is precious,</hi> not onely for his <hi>Benefits,</hi> but for his <hi>Perſon;</hi> that when a <hi>poor Sinner</hi> looks to Chriſt <hi>with an eye of faith,</hi> he looks to Chriſt <hi>with an eye of love</hi> too, and it is in his heart to ſay, <hi>O Lord Jeſus, to whom I come as a poor loſt Sinner, to be waſhed from my ſins with thy blood, I love thee, I prize thee, thou are excellent and glorious: Didſt thou vouchſafe to be manifeſt in the fleſh? Didſt thou come to ſeck and ſave that which was lost? My heart cleaveth to thee in love: And O that I could love thee more, O thou excellent, moſt excellent Lord Jeſus! O thou art fairer then all the children of men, fairer then all the Angels in Heaven! O a Saviour and ſuch a Saviour, the brightneſs of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon! O thy Name is as an Oyntment poured forth! there is none like unto thee: I believe in thee and love thee too, thou art moſt ſweet, thou art altogether lovely, O my dear Lord Jeſus! I firſt caſt mine eyes towards thee as a Redeemer and Saviour, being forced and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to look out for a reſt for my weary Soul, and being a little acquainted with thee, thou haſt taken my heart with thy glorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: O thou art the mighty God, one with the Father; O I be hold ſomething of thy glory, as
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:192261:31"/>of the onely begotten Son of God; thou art God manifest in the fleſh: O 'tis Immanuel, God with us! 'Tis the Lord of glory that was crucified for poor ſinners! He is worthy to be praiſed, he is worthy to be beloved: Bleſſing, and glory, and honour to this great Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour: Praiſe him, O ye Sons of men! Praiſe him all the Angels that excell in ſtrength: How little can I one poor creature do in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and admiring of him. O help, help to praiſe him, help to admire him, help to love him; let every one have a Pſalm of praiſe to him, utter your Songs aloud, aloud ſing Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujahs to this King of glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if any man doth not admire and love the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> neither doth he believe in him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>'Tis an holy Faith,</hi> not onely in regard of the <hi>Object</hi> of it, the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>holy One,</hi> but in regard of the effects of it; <hi>true Faith</hi> is always accompanied with <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> in ſome comfortable meaſure with the principal deſire and endeavour of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Hearts are purified and ſanctified by Faith, for he that doth rightly, looks to Chriſt as a Saviour, ſubmits to him as a Sanctifier alſo; and it is in his heart to ſay, <hi>O Lord Jeſus, thou art a bleſſed Mediatour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:192261:32"/>thou art able not onely to ſave me from the guilt of my ſins but to deliver me from the power of my vile luſts: Come in thou bleſſed of the Lord, come into my heart, ſet up thy Throne there; cast down all my lusts to the ground, turn me from my iniquities, bring into captivity every thought to the obedience of thee, let me be partaker of a ſecond benefit, not onely be juſtified by thee, but ſanctified by thee. Come in thou bleſſed of the Lord, ſtand not without, welcome Chriſt as a Saviour, wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſt as a Sanctifier; thou art he whom my Soul delighteth in, come into thy Temple, drive out all my luſts even all of them, as thou once didſt the Buyers and Sellers out of the Temple; ſhew the power of thy grace, O migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty one, go forth conquering and to conquer, ſubdue mine iniquities, ſtrong is thy arm, ſtrong is thy right hand: let me ſee my deſire upon thine enemies, and my enemies, theſe vile lusts of my heart, ſmite thom to the ground, that they may not riſe a ſecond time until this be perfectly done, and my heart be brought to perfect obedience to thee, I ſhall ſigh and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be at reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we may diſtinguiſh <hi>true Faith,</hi> from <hi>counterfeit Faith that</hi> many have, who while they pretend to <hi>believe on Chriſt</hi> as a <hi>Saviour,</hi> have no intention
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:192261:32"/>and deſire to be <hi>ſanctified</hi> and <hi>walk holily</hi> but rather are more <hi>emboldened to ſin</hi> by ſeeming to lean upon <hi>Chriſt for ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>'Tis an abiding Faith,</hi> true Faith in Chriſt is a <hi>fixed</hi> and <hi>permanent thing.</hi> One that hath but <hi>common workings of the Spirit,</hi> may for a fit in great terrors of conſcience, or at the hearing of a Sermon of Chriſt, ſeem to <hi>believe in Chriſt,</hi> &amp; prize Chriſt above all; but when the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is worne of and thoſe <hi>Common workings of the Spirit</hi> fayle, Chriſt is deſpiſed and made nothing of.</p>
               <p>Though a <hi>Believer</hi> is not alwaies act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Faith</hi> on <hi>Chriſt</hi> yet he hath alwaies the <hi>habit of Faith,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Frame</hi> and <hi>bent</hi> upon his <hi>heart</hi> that though he is not at the preſent under <hi>terrors of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and though his <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> be more reformed then it hath been, yet ſtill he lives upon <hi>Chriſt</hi> as <hi>Jehovah</hi> his <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> not only at the firſt looking to Chriſt but evermore deſiring to <hi>be found in him;</hi> whereas others grow wanton againſt Chriſt when they get out of <hi>terrors of Conſcience,</hi> and think they can do well enough, with their <hi>own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> without his. If a man hath found
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:192261:33"/>that through the <hi>Grace of God</hi> his <hi>heart</hi> hath been carried out in a conſtant way, from time to time, ſince the Lord firſt wrought upon him, ſtill to be humbled for <hi>ſin</hi> and to prize Chriſt, and to live wholly upon his righteouſneſs, it is a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne of <hi>true Faith in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By ſuch things as theſe we may exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our ſelves whether we have <hi>Faith</hi> or no and prove our ſelves whether <hi>Chriſt be in us or not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>ſpecial grace and converſion is frequently called repentance.</hi> Repentan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce <hi>from dead works</hi> Heb. 6.1. <hi>Repentan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, to ſalvation</hi> 2 Cor. 7.10. <hi>God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth men every where to repent</hi> Act. 17.30. <hi>Repent and be converted that your ſins may be blotted out,</hi> Act. 3.19. Then hath God alſo to the Gentiles granted <hi>repentance unto Life,</hi> Act. 11.18. <hi>Him hath God exalted with his right hand to be a prince and a Saviour, to give repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto</hi> Iſrael and forgiveneſs of Sins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore if the Lord hath given a man repentance he is in a ſtate of grace,</hi> and his <hi>ſins are forgiven him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But there is a Legal repentance ſo called; 1. Becauſe it is wrought only by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:192261:33"/>the terrors of the Law and fear of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, 2. Becauſe the perſon that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth onely in that way and manner as to his ſtate and condition, is yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Law</hi> and the curſes of it, and not under <hi>Grace.</hi> Now this is not that which the Scripture calleth <hi>repentance unto Life,</hi> and <hi>repentance unto Salvation</hi> but may be in thoſe that never ſhall be ſaved. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Judas</hi> repented himſelf ſaying, <hi>I have betrayed the innocent blood,</hi> Matth. 27.3, 4. And <hi>Ahab</hi> when he heard of Gods Judgments againſt him, <hi>rent his clothes, put ſackcloth upon his fleſh and faſted and humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> 1 Kings. 21.27.29. yet we find not in the Scripture that he was converted, but the contrary. Men are in nothing more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived then about <hi>Repentance,</hi> deferring it to old age, when they have had their fill of <hi>Sin</hi> as if they were ſure of their lives, as long as they pleaſe to count their time in the world, and as if they could repent at any time when it ſhall pleaſe them to think beſt; and ſo likewiſe many are deceived about their having <hi>Repentance</hi> already, taking e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſigh in a good mood and trouble for their ſins, to be ſufficient <hi>Repentance;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is a <hi>repentance for ſin,</hi> that ariſeth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:192261:34"/>onely from fear of Hell, ſhame in the world, and apprehenſions of outward inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and dangers that men have expoſed themſelves to by their <hi>vile courſes.</hi> What Thief or Murderer except he be extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſtupid and hardened, doth not in ſuch a common way <hi>bewail his ſins,</hi> and yet it may be no ſignes <hi>of true converſion</hi> do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and the perſon wholly ignorant of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>way of ſalvation by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore it is neceſſary to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>common</hi> and <hi>legal repentance,</hi> and that <hi>repentance which is to ſalvation,</hi> which may be done by theſe particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>True repentance is alwaies accompanied with Faith in Chriſt,</hi> ſo that he that doth not <hi>truly believe in Chriſt,</hi> neither doth he <hi>truly repent</hi> Many perſons think if they be but forry for their Sins, that this is enough, and that this will make ſatisfaction for their ſins, and never know what it is to <hi>believe in Chriſt</hi> and to be <hi>waſhed in his blood</hi> from the <hi>guilt of their ſins.</hi> This therefore muſt be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that as when the Scripture ſaith; <hi>believe on the Lord Jeſus and thou ſhalt be ſaved,</hi> it is to be underſtood of ſuch a <hi>Faith</hi> as is accompanied with <hi>repentance and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for ſin:</hi> So when the Lord commandeth us to <hi>repent,</hi> it is to be underſtood of ſuch a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:192261:34"/>
                  <hi>repentance</hi> as is accompanied with <hi>believing in Chriſt,</hi> without which all our ſorrow for ſin, and abſtaining from ſome outward act of it ſignifies nothing. And this is obſervable that ignorant people make <hi>a Chriſt of their repentance,</hi> for they reſt in this, that they are ſorry for their ſins (though the Lord knows the generality of them ſcarce know what <hi>trouble of Conſcience for ſin</hi> is) and never look after Chriſt as a Saviour to <hi>know him</hi> and <hi>believe on his name,</hi> So that their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>repentance</hi> and trouble <hi>for their ſins,</hi> doth but keep them at a diſtance from Chriſt, and maketh them that they hunger and thirſt not after him.</p>
               <p>But where a poor ſinner looks to Chriſt with an <hi>eye of Faith</hi> and <hi>reliance on him,</hi> and looks upon his ſins with <hi>an eye of Sorrow</hi> and grief for them, that is the true <hi>Penitent.</hi> Many are ſo blinded by the God of this world, and the <hi>Goſpel (the way of Salvation by Chriſt)</hi> is ſo hid from them, that all that they look at is, that when they ſin, if they be but ſorry for it, and purpoſe to amend they think that all is well, and that God is pacified for all that they have done againſt him, and are ſtrangers all their dayes to believing in Chriſt and being accepted in him.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:192261:35"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>True repentance is a ſorrowing for ſin, as it is an offending and diſpleaſing God;</hi> and not mearly for the hurt and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief that <hi>Sin</hi> hath brought or may bring upon our lives. Indeed as we are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſaid in the Scripture, <hi>to ſin againſt God;</hi> ſo we are ſaid to be <hi>Sinners againſt our own ſouls,</hi> Num. 16.38. As <hi>ſin</hi> is an offence it is committed againſt God, but the hurt and miſchief of it is to our own ſouls, and upon both theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, we are to <hi>repent</hi> of it: but it is not godly ſorrow that we have for our ſins, except we have a reſpect to God grieving that we have violated his <hi>Laws</hi> and ſo offended his <hi>Bleſſed Majeſty,</hi> as well as that we have wronged our own <hi>Souls,</hi> and deſtroyed our <hi>ſelves</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out he prevent it by ſhewing us <hi>mercy in Chriſt.</hi> So that it is in the heart of a true Penitent to ſigh out ſuch <hi>lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> as theſe; <hi>O moſt glorious God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, againſt thee have I ſinned, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee my Creator, from whom I have my being, againſt thee the pure and holy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, holy, holy, holy, against thee, who art the Lord God, gracious, long ſuffering, and abundant in mercy, O thou infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, O thou Father of mercies, againſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:192261:35"/>thee have I ſinned, I have tranſgreſſed, I have rebelled, and I, whither ſhall I cauſe my ſhame to go, I cannot put it away from mee, for to mee belongeth ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Face, becauſe I have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, I cannot ſtand before thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my ſins, but through the blood of Jeſus. Lord I cannot abaſe my ſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough before thee, nor be vile enough in my own eyes. I ſee a little of thee, what a bleſſed and glorious Majeſty thou art whom I have offended, and I ſee a little of my ſelf, that behold I am vile, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I abhor my ſelf in duſt and aſhes: O that thou would'ſt make my head as waters and mine eyes as a Fountain of tears to weep day and night for my ſins: O that thou wouldſt ſmite and ſpeak to this Rock of my heart, that the waters of godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row might guſh out: O that thy Spirit might work more upon me this way to give me a more broken and contrite Spirit for ſin, I do not deſire thou ſhouldſt ſpeak any more to my Soul from Mount Sinai with thoſe Thunderings and Lightenings, and that terrible voice out of the fire and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and tempeſts preſenting thy wrath to mee for the breach of thy holy Law but now thou haſt brought my poor weary fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:192261:36"/>ſoul to Jeſus the Mediator and to the blood of sprinkling, speak to me from the mercy ſeat, ſpeak comfortably to me, melt and ſoften my heart, with the ſight of thy grace in Chriſt, and let my ſoul be filled with that Sorrow for Sin that is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with the ſenſe of pardon in Chriſt, which ſorrow is moſt genuine, filial, free, and acceptable unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>True repentance is accompanied with the hatred of ſin.</hi> David a true penitent hated <hi>every falſe way,</hi> Pſal. 119.128. <hi>Paul</hi> in his <hi>Lamentations</hi> for the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of corruption in him ſaith; that which I hate, That do I, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15. a true Penitent not onely mournes for ſin committed but hates it, abhors it from his New Nature; he hath an everlaſting An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripathy againſt <hi>Sin,</hi> that if the Principle of grace in him was not hindred in its actings by <hi>Sin</hi> that dwelleth in him, a true Penitent would ſhew himſelf ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner of perſon then he doth: we muſt not think that after true repentance a man ſinneth no more for there is no man that liveth here below and <hi>Sinneth</hi> not; neither muſt wee think that ſuch a one may not poſſibly fall into the ſame <hi>Sin</hi> againe. Indeed for groſs Sins, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:192261:36"/>God keeps his people from them, from the time of their <hi>firſt converſion</hi> and if he leave them to falll into them at any time; as he did <hi>Noah, David</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> after particular repentance for them, and recovery out of them, it is a rare and unuſual thing for them to fall into them again, but as for <hi>vain thoughts, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions in holy duties</hi> and <hi>paſſions,</hi> and ſuch Sins as do ſuddenly Surpriſe and overtake us as at unawares no doubt after <hi>true repentance</hi> a godly Man may fall into them again and again, to the great grief of his Soul; yea after much repentance particularly for thoſe things and many <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>ſupplications</hi> to God for power and ſtrength againſt them ſo that not once or twice, but often and every day the beſt <hi>Saints</hi> have need with <hi>Paul</hi> to cry out, O <hi>wretched Man that I am who ſhall deliver me from this body of death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all this remainder of corruption that the beſt <hi>Saints</hi> upon earth will confeſs, there is yet in them as <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf complained (though ignorant and proud <hi>Phariſees</hi> that know not themſelves, and the plague of their owne hearts think themſelves to be perfect) yet I ſay
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:192261:37"/>this truth abideth firme, that a <hi>true pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent</hi> hateth <hi>Sin,</hi> it is beſides his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is againſt the general purpoſe of his heart, it is contrary to his new na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and 'tis the grief of his Soul when he <hi>Sinneth againſt God;</hi> he ſo hateth ſin, that he will never be at peace with it but oppoſeth it and looks to Heaven it ſelf for aid againſt the enemy.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>True repentance is an abiding thing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heart,</hi> not that a <hi>true Penitent</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways acting the <hi>grace of Repentance;</hi> but though it may ceaſe ſometimes in the <hi>act,</hi> yet it never ceaſes in the <hi>habit:</hi> that is, there is always in ſuch, an <hi>habitual frame</hi> upon the heart to live low before God, and walk humbly with him.</p>
               <p>A <hi>natural man</hi> may ſometimes in great <hi>afflictions,</hi> and in <hi>terrours of Conſcience</hi> mourn for ſin, but 'tis a forced thing, he would get it off from his ſpirit, and it leaves not an <hi>habitual humiliation</hi> upon him, but that <hi>filial, evangelical ſorrow</hi> that a <hi>Believer</hi> hath for ſin, is a <hi>frame of spirit</hi> that he likes and loves, and cheriſheth, and would have more of, for (which is a great myſtery to a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man) that kind of ſorrow for ſin that a man in the ſtate of grace hath, may be accompanied with the greateſt ſenſe and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:192261:37"/>aſſurance of <hi>pardon in Christ,</hi> and ſo be a very ſweet and pleaſing, and deſirable <hi>frame of spirit.</hi> At the ſame time a <hi>poor ſoul</hi> may rejoyce in Gods pardoning grace in Chriſt, and mourn for ſin too; and a poor broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted <hi>Believer</hi> finds this ſorrow to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſweeter then all the laughter and merriment of the men of the World.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Special Grace and Converſion is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently called in the Scripture, the Fear of God.</hi> Job's character is, <hi>that he was a man that feared God,</hi> Job 1.1. <hi>Obadiah's, That he feared the Lord greatly,</hi> 1 Kings 18.3. Let us hear the concluſion of the whole mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Fear God and keep his Commandments, for this is the whole duty of man,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.13. <hi>Praiſe our God all ye his ſervants, and ye that fear him,</hi> Rev. 19.5. <hi>The Lord taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them that fear him,</hi> Pſalm. 147.11. And it is one great promiſe of God in the New Covenant, <hi>to put his fear into our hearts,</hi> Jerem. 32.40. So that where there is a right fear of God, there is <hi>true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But becauſe there is a common awe of a Deity in moſt men, a certain ſlaviſh, ſervile, fear of God, ſearing him, only as a Male factor feareth the Judge, not as a dutiful
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:192261:38"/>Son feareth a good Father, and that upon judgments that God ſends, ſome are ſaid, <hi>to fear the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.32, 33. that is, <hi>with a ſlaviſh fear,</hi> yet <hi>v.</hi> 34. 'tis ſaid of the ſame perſons, <hi>They fear not the Lord, nor do after his Statutes;</hi> that is, they had not a gracious and obedient fear of God: And likewiſe becauſe the very Devils are ſaid <hi>to tremble,</hi> Jam. 2.19. that is, they even ſhake with fear of the <hi>wrath of God;</hi> therefore it is neceſſary to diſtinguiſh between that ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh fear of God that is in the very wicked of the World, and in the Devils themſelves, and that right gracious fear of God that is in thoſe that are truly <hi>converted,</hi> which may be done in theſe following particulars:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>A right fear of God is accompanied with hope in his free mercy in Chriſt.</hi> The Lord taketh pleaſure in them that fear him, in thoſe that hope in his mercy, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 147.11. Some they pretend to hope in Gods mercy in Chriſt, but they do not fear God, their hearts are not awed with his Majeſty, nor afraid to offend him: ſuch a hope is not right; on the other hand, ſome pretend to fear God, and fear ſinning a gainſt him, but they hope not in his mercy, but in their own merits; they go on under a <hi>Covenant of works,</hi> caſt not their Souls upon Chriſt
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:192261:38"/>will not lay their hold upon the hope that is ſet before them in the Goſpel. Theſe men have not a right fear of God: He that is ſo moved with fear of the Majeſty and Wrath of God, that he gets into Chriſt, the Ark that God hath prepared for the ſaving of Souls, and placeth all his hope for his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſafety in Chriſt the Son of God; this is the man that feareth the Lord aright. But if men fear God only as a Judge and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger of Sin, and look upon him as a hard Maſter, and ſo are afraid of him, and their hearts ſecretly riſe againſt him, but they never look towards his Mercy-ſeat, that they may ſet their hope in his grace in Chriſt, ſuch have not a right fear of God, neither a right reverential, nor a right filial fear of God, but onely a ſlaviſh and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>A right fear of God is accompanied with eſchewing evil. Job</hi> is ſaid to be a man <hi>fearing God and eſchewing evil,</hi> Job. 1.1. <hi>The tranſgreſſion of the wicked ſaith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my heart, that there is no fear of God before his eyes,</hi> Pſalm, 36.1. The groſs and horrible profaneneſs of ſome wicked men proclaims to every one, that they are ſo far from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a right fear of God, ſuch as he puts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:192261:39"/>the hearts of his people, that they have no fear of God, no common awe of a Deity at all in their ordinary courſe, for they live as if there were no God that regarded the ways of the Sons of men, and would bring them into judgment: But where there is a right fear of God, there is not a bare eſchewing evil, but an eſchewing evil from an inward principle of the fear and love of God in the heart, and delight in his Commandments.</p>
               <p>Now when eſchewing evil is made a ſign of the true fear of God in the heart, it muſt not be ſo underſtood, as if <hi>Job</hi> of whom that character is given in the place above-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned or any other (who yet truly fear God) can ſo totally eſchew evil in this life, as to be wholly free from ſin; for we ſee by the holy Story, that <hi>Job</hi> himſelf of whom this is ſpoken, had his paſſions and ſinful fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, for which he confeſſed to God he was <hi>vile, and abhorred himſelf in duſt and aſhes;</hi> but when ſuch are ſaid to eſchew evil, the meaning is, that they do ſo in a comfortable meaſure, and in the ſincere and earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and endeavour of their Souls.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>A right fear of God is not an involun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary paſſion and fear which torments the mind, but is a pleaſing and delightful thing to the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:192261:39"/>Soul. Fear hath torment,</hi> 1 John 4.18. Slaviſh, ſinful and irregular fear hath ſo; but a right reverential fear of God is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful to the Soul, it hath no torment in it to the mind. The Angels in Heaven, and the Saints in all their glory have an high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of this reverential fear of God. And ſo they find here in this World, that they never have ſweeter duties, then when their hearts are moſt filled with a reverential fear of God, and ſo in their whole converſation they find that the more they walk in the fear of the Lord, the more they walk in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Indeed in ſuch extraordinary appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God by outward ſigns of the Glory of his Majeſty, as were to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 15.12.17. to <hi>Moſes</hi> when the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the <hi>flame of fire out of the midſt of the buſh,</hi> Exod. 3.2. &amp; 6. to <hi>Elijah,</hi> 1 Kings 19.13. and to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> Chap. 6.5. the beſt Saint in this mortal ſtate may be over-ſet and faint, and be troubled at the Lords pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; for 'tis ſaid, that when God ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Abraham,</hi> an horrour of great darkneſs fell upon him: 'tis ſaid of <hi>Moſes, he hid his face, and was afraid to look upon God,</hi> and at another time when God ſpake out of the fire upon Mount <hi>Sinai, Moſes</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:192261:40"/>ſaid, <hi>I exceedingly fear and tremble.</hi> Elijah <hi>hid his face in his Mantie:</hi> and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> cries out, <hi>Wo is me, I am undone, for mine eyes have ſeen the King, the Lord of hoſts.</hi> But it is to be conſidered, that it was not meerly the apprehenſion of the greatneſs and glory of the Majeſty of God, and the reverence of God thereupon, that cauſed this trouble to their ſpirits, but theſe extraordinary ſigns of Gods preſence, which their bodies and ſpirits in this frail and mortal ſtate could not bear. That nevertheleſs it ſtands good what hath been laid down, that a reverential fear of God is a moſt pleaſing and delightful thing to the Soul of a Chriſtian, yea it helps much to compoſe the body and natural ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in the ſervice of God, and walking with him.</p>
               <p>In a word, to diſtinguiſh a right feare of God from a ſlaviſh or hipocriticall feare, it is of that nature, that the more we feare him, the more we hope in his mercy, the more we feare him, the more obedient we are to him; the more we fear him, the more we would fear him, and deſire to feare his Name, and the more we fear him, the more we love him: he that findeth in any meaſure ſuch a feare of God put into his heart as is here deſcribed, is converted and in the ſtate of grace.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:192261:40"/>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Speciall grace and converſion</hi> is held forth in the Scripture by <hi>love to God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3. <hi>If any man love God, the ſame is known of him,</hi> Epheſ. 6.24. <hi>Grace be with all them that love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity.</hi> John. 21.17. <hi>Simon Son of Jonas loveſt thou me?</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Lord thou knoweſt all things, thou knoweſt that I love thee.</hi> Men may have notional knowledge, parts and gifts, and this may but puffe them up with pride and do their ſouls no good; but if a man ſo know God as to love him and delight in him, that is the man that is known of God, owned and approved of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> what are the ſignes of love to God.</p>
               <p>Anſw. 1 <hi>High and raiſed thoughts of God fixed and ſetled in the heart, are a ſigne of love to God; an habituall frame of heart to look upon God as moſt excellent and glorious, and to adore him as well for his holineſs and infinite purity, as for the exceeding riches of his grace in Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, a Saints love to God is not come to perfection in this life, it is not come to its height by a Thouſand degrees, yet there is ſuch an impreſſion of love to God upon the heart of a Believer and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:192261:41"/>other things, for his wonderful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of grace in Chriſt, that he thinks (and well he may) that he can never love and prayſe the holy Lord as he ſhould do. And ſometimes it may be his heart waxes hot, and this fire of love to God burneth and flameth in him, and he can cry out to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, Oh, <hi>O Lord, how excellent is thy name in all the earth,</hi> and thy glory is above the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; <hi>Look, Look, O my ſoul, upon this great King, the King of glory, the King eternal and immortal, and admire him and love him for ever. O thou infinite goodneſs, O thou Fountain of Life, wilt thou vouchſafe to be loved of me? O thy condiſcention, thy condiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that thou wilt not account it preſumption for me to love thee, ſuch a poor worm as I am &amp; ſo vile and ſinful! O bleſſed Lord, if I may love thee, then O my baſe unworthineſs that I love thee no more! O love, love flame out, flame out, here is thy right object, this is he that is to be loved with all my heart, with all my Soul, with all my might and with all my ſtrength; here is infinite power, here is infinite wiſdom, here is infinite holineſs, here is infinite mercy; more love, more, more love for the holy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed lord: what ſhall I love him no more, O my ſoul, are thy faculties enlarged to love as far as a poor finite creature is capable to love?
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:192261:41"/>O my ſoul, love as Jehovah is to be loved, love ſuitably to the Object thou art now ſet upon, love not as if thou wert loving a creature, love not at ſuch a poor and low rate, but love as one that is loving an infinite and glorious God; love as one that is loving him that is love it ſelf, and hath manifeſted it in ſending his only begotten Son into the world to ſave ſinners. O what manner of love was this, and O with what manner of love ſhould this bleſſed God be loved? O Lord thou art above all love, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all praiſe! O that ever I have loved any thing elſe beſides thee, when there was thy ſelf to love! O that ever I ſhould love ſuch a vile thing as ſin, and ſuch a poor trifle as the world is! Lord now ſet my love right, put my heart in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the higheſt pitch of love to thee that poor clay is capable of, and there hold me to eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus poſſibly a poor Believer may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times finde his heart rayſed to God in love and delight in him; however there is a root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, grounded, ſetled affection in the ſoul of a Believer to God, ſo that he doth not only ſee reaſon why he ſhould love God, but it is his deſire to love him and delight in him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things, though the actings of this love may be much kept down by maniſold temptations and by the oppoſition of the fleſh, as the actings of other graces in us are alſo.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:192261:42"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Hating of ſin becauſe God hates it,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is diſpleaſing to him, is a ſigne of love to God, <hi>ye that love the Lord hate evil,</hi> Pſal. 97.10. it is not onely their duty to do ſo, but in ſome meaſure it is ſo <hi>with</hi> every Child of God.</p>
               <p>Though after <hi>converſion</hi> ſin doth yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, it is hated and abhorred ſo, that it is in the heart to ſay, <hi>O Sin what doſt thou here? thou art not</hi> onely my <hi>greateſt enemy, but thou art an enemy to that holy and bleſſed God whom my ſoul loveth. O when ſhall I be rid of thee? time was when thou and I were all one, we were wedded together, but now I ſee it was an unlawful marriage, I was to be for the Lord and not for another, therefore I will love thee no more: O if it be ſo that thou wilt not leave me, till death us do part, I wait for that good hour when the Lord will take me to himſelf, that ſo I may be freed from thee wholly and for ever, and be with my heavenly Head and husband.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Love to the Saints is a ſign of love to God,</hi> he that ſaith, he loveth <hi>God and hateth his Brother is a lyar; he that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen how can he love God, whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> 1 John 4.20. He that loveth not the Image of God in grace and holineſs, which he ſeeth in his people how
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:192261:42"/>can he love God, whom in his glorious eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence he hath not ſeen. An univerſal love to all in whom we ſee the grace of Chriſt, is a certain ſign of our love to God: ſo that one that truly loves God, can in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure appeal to God, to this effect; <hi>O Lord, however I have hated thy people in time past, and my heart hath ſecretly riſen againſt them, for the good that was in them, yet ſince thou haſt been pleaſed to turn me from darkneſs to light, I make an high account of thy people, I look upon them as the excellent on the earth; I am troubled that I love them no more, and that I can do no more for them; I love them not meerly becauſe they are of my judgment in ſome leſſer points, but I love them becauſe they fear and love thee, becauſe they repent of their ſinning againſt thee, and believe on thy Son, and deſire to walk ſo as to pleaſe thee, ſo far as thou art pleaſed to give them the knowledge of thy will: My heart is knit to them, whoſe hearts are knit to Chriſt, who cleave in their hearts to that one Mediatour, that one Offering, that one Sacrifice for ſins for ever, ſo far as they manifeſt this, they are dear to me, they muſt needs be precious to me, to whom Chriſt is precious. And though becauſe of ſome errours and miſtakes that in my poor thoughts I may judge ſome of them to be in, I cannot comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:192261:43"/>joyn with ſuch in ſome things; yet O Lord, thou that knoweſt all things, knowest that I love them, and though through paſſion and ignorance, and miſguided zeal, I may carry it unſcemly ſometimes to ſome of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and have a hand in their troubles and ſufferings, (as it is poſſible for the Saints in ſome ſort to perſecute one another in this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect ſtate) yet O Lord, thou knowest that my heart is not ſet againſt any of them, for that which I judge to be good in them, but do love and honour them for it. And though my love is moſt exerciſed and drawn out to thoſe Saints whom I am moſt acquainted with, and to whom I am neareſt joyned in the fellowſhip of the Gospel, there being more occaſion and opportunity for the drawing out of my love to them; yet thou knoweſt there is love in my heart to all Saints, and there is not that man living that makes profeſſion of thy Name, though differing from me in opinion, and violent againſt me, of whom I ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce to have thoughts of meeting him in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if men be Deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, hate them, and ſpeak evil of them falſly for Chriſts ſake, though they may flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themſelves, and think they love God, yet they do not. They that ſcoff at the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:192261:43"/>Godly, and their hearts riſe againſt them for their grace and holineſs, though they will ſay they love God, or elſe it were pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they ſhould live, they are utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, for indeed they are Haters of God and Goodneſs. Many other ſigns of love to God might here be mentioned, as grieving when God is diſhonoured, longing for the coming of his Kingdom, that his Name, and Truth, and Glory may be more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the World, and deſiring to bring all that we can to love him and obey him.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe many other expreſſions by which Converſion is ſet forth in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, might be opened, but theſe things that have been ſpoken, may ſuffice to ſhew wherein Converſion lieth, if God give men hearts to examine their ſpiritual eſtate, which ſhall read theſe things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:192261:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the Outward Means that God is pleaſed to make uſe of in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Souls.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat God doth make uſe of outward means in the bringing of Souls home to himſelf, is evident both from Scripture and Experience, which is not becauſe God cannot do the work without Outward Means (for in Elect Infants, and ſometimes in others, God worketh Grace without them) but it is meerly from the pleaſure of his will, what way he will take to convert a ſoul, and whatſoever the outward means be, the inward, ſpiritual and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual means of Converſion is, the Almighty Power of God, as I intend to ſet forth in the next Chapter.</p>
               <p>But to give ſome account of this matter, concerning the outward means that the Lord makes uſe of for the converſion of ſouls.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Sometimes the Lord hath made uſe of great and ſore afflictions to awaken men, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them of their ſins, and ſo to bring them
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:192261:44"/>to Chriſt:</hi> And if they be bound in Fetters, and be holden in Cords of affliction, then he ſheweth them their work and their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions that they have exceeded, he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth their ear to Diſcipline, <hi>Job</hi> 36.8, 9. <hi>Job</hi> 33.19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24. As one who being ſick and reſtleſs ſome nights, it pleaſed God to put in with the affliction, and ſet this upon his heart, that if it were ſo grievous to him to paſs away a few Nights, though he was in his own Houſe, and amongſt his dear Relations, becauſe he had pain and ſickneſs upon his body, how miſerable ſhould he be if he ſhould bear the torments of Hell for ever; and ſo the Lord brought him to look after an intereſt in Chriſt, that he might be <hi>delivered from the wrath to come.</hi> The Lord ſometimes makes uſe of ſhame in the World, poverty, impriſonment, yea the ſentence of death, to be the means of bringing men to a ſight of their ſins, and to look after Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Sometimes the holy and convincing lives of the Saints,</hi> have been bleſſed of God, to put ignorant and wicked men upon enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after Religion, ſaying within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Surely there is an excellency in the ways of God,; ſurely in thoſe ways muſt I find bleſſedneſs and peace, and not in theſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:192261:45"/>ways of debauchery and profaneneſs:</hi> And ſo the Lord lets in light into their ſouls; and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts godly Wives to <hi>carry themſelves with that holineſs and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspection, that their carnal husbands who it may be are ſo obſtinate and profane, that they will ſcarce hear the faithful preaching of the word, may without that means be won by their heavenly converſation,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We read of many that in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times when ſuch great multitudes laid down their lives for the Name of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>by beholding their patience and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in their ſufferings, were convinced of the truth and excellency of Chriſtian Religion, and were converted unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Some obſerving how earneſtly godly Miniſters or others have wraſtled with God in Prayer for their converſion, have been awakened by it, and God hath put it into their hearts, to think with themſelves, that if the ſalvation of their Souls be ſo much ſet by in the eyes of others, how much more ſhould the ſalvation of their Souls be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by themſelves; and upon ſuch thoughts the Lord hath begun the <hi>good work in them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>hearing of the great horrour of Conſcience, that others are in for ſin,</hi> and tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:192261:45"/>with them about the cauſe of their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, hath been bleſſed of God to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of ſome. This hath convinced ſome that were almoſt <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> that there is a God and that it is a fearful thing to lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſenſe of his wrath; this hath put them upon looking into their owne eſtate, and ſo brought them to Chriſt, and ſo they have found that it was better to heare the ſhrieks, and cryes, and groans of thoſe that were heavy laden with the ſenſe of their ſins, then to hear the jollity, merriment and ſongs of fools, and ſpiritual Mad-Men who go laughing to Hell.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>The Inſtructions of Parents and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> have been oftentimes bleſſed of God, to the converſion of their Children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: Godly Parents as their Children grow up, ſhould deſire to be inſtruments of bringing their Children to Heaven, as well as they were inſtruments to bring them into this World. And ſome Children bleſs God that they had praying Fathers, and praying Mothers, and ſuch as taught them the fear of the Lord. <hi>Some ſervants bleſs God that ever they came to live in Praying Families, and where they were instructed in the wayes of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God ſometimes brings to remembrance the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:192261:46"/>inſtructions of Parents and Maſters, to do their Children and ſervants good, when they are at reſt in the duſt; even thoſe inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which when they were firſt given, took no impreſſion upon them.</hi> That the good ſeed which they had ſowne, and could not ſee any effect of, the Lord watereth it by his Spirit: when they are dead and gone, then to their Children remember the words which were ſpoken unto them, and they come with new life and Power upon their hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To theſe many more might be added, but let me come to ſpeak of that which is the moſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way of converſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>The word preached is the moſt ordinary means of converſion;</hi> the reading of the word our ſelves, or hearing it read by others, and likewiſe the reading of other good Books, have been bleſſed of God to the converſion of Souls, and all theſe things are to be uſed: But the opening, urging, and applying the doctrine of the word unto people in a way of preaching is the ordinary means of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.37.41. <hi>Acts.</hi> 11.21.22. <hi>Acts.</hi> 26.16, 17, 18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Go teach all nations.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.2. <hi>Preach the word, be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</hi> Rom. 10. <hi>How ſhall they believe on him of whom they have not heard, and how ſhall
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:192261:46"/>they hear without a preacher.</hi> And ſo it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth throughout the ſtory of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, that the declaring of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by lively voice was the great means that God made uſe of for the Converſion of Souls.</p>
               <p>And here it is to be noted, That thoſe who are converted out of this ordinary way, whatſoever outward means the Lord plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to take occaſion by, for their converſion; yet he doth, (though more immediately by his Spirit,) ſet home the ſame things (for the ſubſtance) upon their hearts that are held forth to others, who are converted by the Miniſtry of the word, that is, the Lord ſhewes them their ſinful and miſerable eſtate, and reveals Chriſt to them, as the only way of juſtification and acceptance with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now then ſeeing God is Pleaſed to make ſo much uſe of the preaching of the word for the converſion of Souls; let all the true miniſters of Chriſt go forth in his name, and ſtrength, let them look to him for aſſistance and ſucceſs in the work, and as ever they would be Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental for the converſion of Souls, let them preach with all plaineſs of Speech, let them not be deſirous of vain glory; let them Preach without all oſtentation, without all dark and affected expreſſions, and let them in their
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:192261:47"/>Preaching inſiſt much upon common and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental truths, as about the greatneſs and holineſs of God, the ſinfulneſs and miſery of Man; The neceſſity of converſion and the way of redemption by the blood of Jeſus.</hi> Such ſubjects as theſe are ſo vaſt, and alſo ſo neceſſary that they may take up much of a Miniſters Preaching: It is a great fault in miniſters if they do not with all their might, ſet forth unto men their miſerable eſtate by nature, and if they do not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to bring their hearers acquainted with Chriſt? <hi>holding forth him upon all occaſions to them, not only as he by whom we muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered from the wrath to come, but as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and Spring of all grace, and Spiritual ſtrength, whereby we may walk in holineſs, and new obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For Miniſters to put men upon for ſaking their evil wayes and ſo promiſing them Life without directing them to Chriſt, to put their whole truſt in him, for their juſtification; and to fetch ſtrength and vertue from him, for the mortification of Sin and for new obedience, is but to teach men to build upon the Sands, and to ſhew them a cleaner way to Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For Miniſters to preach ſo much at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, not having well digeſted themſelves the doctrine of original Sin, the difference,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:192261:47"/>between the Law and the Goſpel, the nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſity and nature of converſion, the doctrine of juſtification by the righteouſneſs of Chriſt imputed to them that believe, and the nature of Goſpel grace and true ſanctification, tends to the making of their Preaching uſeleſs to the ſalvation of mens Souls: And though ſuch Preachers may have applauſe from the ignorant for their <hi>Method,</hi> delivery and learning, yet they do but miſlead men and trifle with them about a thing of the higheſt moment, the ſalvation of their Souls.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As a Phyſician muſt not play with the life of a man, 'Tis ſuch a precious thing, but had need to be well adviſed in his Judgment of the nature of the diſeaſe and of a right Method for cure, and haue many things in his eye; ſo had a Miniſter need to be careful</hi> much more, in dealing with ſuch a thing as the Soul of a man is, to know the original cauſe of Soul <hi>Ma ladies,</hi> and the only way of cure, which is by the blood of Jeſus. <hi>But if Preachers do but play with their Texts, and play with the Souls of their hearers, not having their hearts awed with a holy reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God and his Word, and affectiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely deſirous of the eternal ſalvation of the People, great is their Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:192261:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>What with the differences amongſt us about leſſer things, and invectives that Preachers ſtuff their Sermons with, againſt thoſe that diſſent from them; what with errors of Doctrine, that ſome Preachers ſeem to be tainted with; what with the new coyned words and Phantaſtical expreſſions that ſome preachers uſe: and what with want of experience in their own ſouls, of the nature of converſion: it is to be feared there is a great decay of ſound, plain and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preaching, eſpecially about the points of juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiation and converſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next to erroneous preaching 'tis moſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive to an intelligent, and ſpiritual hearer, when a Miniſter preacheth with high words, affecting ſuch a ſtile as is no way ſuited to the profit of his hearers. And though ſuch may admire themſelves, and alſo have their reward, that is, applauſe of the ignorant, yet their preaching is nauſeated of the judicious. It is a more difficult thing, and requireth more ſubſtantial learning, to ſet forth the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Goſpel, to the capacity of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary hearers, then to ſtuff Sermons with quotations, Scraps of <hi>Latin</hi> and School tearms, made ready to our hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But it may be ſaid, ſeeing that the habit of grace and ſpiritual Life is infuſed into the Soul by the spirit of God</hi> (as hath been
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:192261:48"/>ſhewn:) <hi>when a Soul is converted by the preaching of the word, how doth the Lord ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect this work thereby?</hi> Anſwer, 1. Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>It is not the holineſs of the Preacher that doth convert the Hearers.</hi> All that heard Chriſt himſelf preach, the <hi>holieſt Preacher</hi> that ever was, were not <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>It is not the affections of the Preacher that doth convert the Hearers;</hi> his Zeal and his Compaſſion to the Souls of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are very good, and God is pleaſed ſo to work, that ſometimes the <hi>affections of the Preachers</hi> do affect the hearts of the Hearers; but except the Lord put in, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is done, all his weeping will not break their hearts and reclaim them from their ſins.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>It is not meerly the ſublimity and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the matter that is preached, that doth convert the Hearers, for then all ſhould be converted that hear the Gospel preached.</hi> It may be the perſon that is <hi>converted</hi> at a <hi>Sermon,</hi> hath heard the ſame <hi>Points</hi> opened many a time, and that more fully then at that time, yet was never <hi>affected</hi> till now; the <hi>Reaſon is,</hi> becauſe now <hi>God ſpeaketh to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:192261:49"/>his heart,</hi> as well as the <hi>Minister to his ear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>It is not the excellency of ſpeech or wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Preacher that doth convert the Hearers.</hi> All the Oratory in the World cannot convert a Soul: Arguments, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, Threatnings, and Intreaties ſet forth with the Tongues of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> (if they were to aſſume humane ſhape and ſpeak to Sinners) about their <hi>everlasting concernments,</hi> could not prevail to bring them from <hi>Sin to Chriſt,</hi> except the Lord put forth his <hi>Almighty power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>It is not from any power of Nature that before lay dormient and idle, that now awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and yieldeth obedience to the Word that a Soul is converted:</hi> For there is no ſuch power of Nature, 'tis an idle ſpeculation of thoſe that think it is ſo; for in <hi>converſion</hi> the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God is put into us, and the fear of God, (and ſo conſequently the Seed and Principle of Faith, and Repentance, and other Graces) is put into our hearts where before it was not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Poſitively I anſwer, <hi>That the efficacy, power and vertue of the preaching of the Word when a Soul is converted by it, is wholly from the Spirit of God.</hi> When the Scripture ſaith,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:192261:49"/>
                  <hi>That faith cometh by hearing,</hi> 'tis only as an outward means that God worketh by, when it pleaſes him: for bare hearing of the Goſpel worketh Faith in no man, for <hi>Faith is the gift of God,</hi> Epheſ. 2.8. Philip. 1.29. <hi>The fruit of the Spirit,</hi> Galat. 5.22.</p>
               <p>And when the <hi>Gospel</hi> is ſaid <hi>to be the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God unto ſalvation;</hi> it is not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood as if the bare preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel did ſave and convert men, but it is called <hi>the power of God unto ſalvation,</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Covenant of works,</hi> becauſe it reveals and holds forth the way of Grace in Chriſt, by which God ſaveth loſt Sinners, which the Law doth not. How the Spirit of God doth work in and by the preaching of the Word for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of Souls, is a deep myſtery. And O that we may experimentally know that the Holy Ghoſt hath made uſe of the Word to convert our Souls, though we cannot exactly conceive of the way and manner of his working thereby. The workings of the Holy Ghoſt in <hi>Converſion</hi> are compared to <hi>the wind,</hi> as for the freeneſs and powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſo for the myſtery that is in them: <hi>As the wind bloweth where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof, but canst not tell
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:192261:50"/>whence it cometh and whither it goeth, ſo is every one that is born of the Spirit,</hi> John 3.8.</p>
               <p>But for further light into this Queſtion, let us obſerve theſe Scriptures following: It is ſaid, <hi>The Lord opened the heart of</hi> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia <hi>that ſhe attended to the things that were ſpoken by</hi> Paul: Miniſters do but <hi>call</hi> and <hi>knock</hi> at the doors of mens hearts, 'tis God that by a ſecret work of his Spirit openeth their hearts, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14. And it is ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.44. <hi>While</hi> Peter <hi>yet ſpake theſe words, the Holy Ghoſt fell on all them that heard him. Peters</hi> preaching, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſts falling upon them that heard him, were two diſtinct things, the one might have been without the other, the one was <hi>the work of man,</hi> the other was <hi>the work of God.</hi> And that which is ſaid, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5. will make it yet far more evident, <hi>For our Gospel came not unto you in word only, but in power and in the Holy Ghoſt, and in much aſſurance:</hi> The Goſpels coming to people in word, and in the bare preaching of it, is one thing, and the Goſpels coming to them in power and in the Holy Ghoſt, is another: to ſome the <hi>Gospel</hi> comes only in word, they hear a ſound of words, and as they are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:192261:50"/>men, they may have a notional know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof; but unto the Elect it comes with power and with the Holy Ghoſt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with ſuch powerful workings of the Spirit, as turns them from Sin to Chriſt. Of theſe things this is the ſum, the preaching of the Word ſhews us the way of <hi>ſalvation,</hi> it is the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> that by a ſecret and ſtrong hand puts us into that way: The <hi>preaching of the Word</hi> ſhews us <hi>our loſt eſtate by Nature,</hi> it is the Spirit that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly makes us ſenſible of it, and affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our hearts with it: The <hi>preaching of the Word</hi> ſhews us <hi>Gods Grace in Chriſt,</hi> holds up <hi>Christ</hi> as the <hi>Brazen Serpent;</hi> it is the <hi>Spirit</hi> that gives us an <hi>eye of faith,</hi> to look to him that we may live: The coming to the Ordinance to hear the Word, is like the Woman in the Goſpel, <hi>touching the hem of Chriſts garment,</hi> others touched him as well as ſhe; but there came a ſecret ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from Chriſt to heal her of her <hi>Bloody Iſſue.</hi> Many come to the <hi>preaching of the Word,</hi> and to ſome of their Souls there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>ſecret vertue from Chriſt,</hi> that they find in themſelves, that now they are humbled for ſin, now they prize Chriſt, now they cleave unto the Lord with a full purpoſe of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:192261:51"/>heart to walk in his ways: <hi>Praiſe the Lord for ever.</hi> It was not the Miniſter, it was not the bare preaching of the Word, that could make this change; but this was <hi>the day of the Lords power to thy Soul,</hi> and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue came ſecretly from our <hi>bleſſed Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> to thy Soul, admire him, and love him, and cleave to him, to carry thee on by the ſame power of his Spirit unto the end. It may be many others in the ſame Sermon found no vertue come from Chriſt to their Souls, it was a burden and tedious to them: <hi>Admire free Grace, and love the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we find good to our Souls by the <hi>preaching of the Word,</hi> we muſt not look upon poor Miniſters with admiration of them, as if by their power and holineſs we had ſuch a change wrought in us; but know, <hi>that God hath made bare his own arm,</hi> and <hi>glorified his own power and the exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riches of his grace in Chriſt Jeſus to us<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is one reaſon why God makes uſe many times of perſons of meaner parts and ſmall repute, to be Inſtruments of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting more Souls, than he doth of others that excel them, that it may appear that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:192261:51"/>the high and excellent power that converts the Soul, is of God and not of man. It is not fit that <hi>the Glory of God</hi> ſhould be given to Miniſters and Ordinances, if we get any good to our Souls by them, look upon them but as <hi>the Conduit-pipes,</hi> and let all the <hi>Glory be given to him who is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of life; for thine, O Lord, is the Kingdom, and the Power, and the Glory for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:192261:52"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CONVERSION</hi> Wrought by the <hi>POWER</hi> of <hi>GOD</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Shewing that whatſoever Outward Means the Lord makes uſe of for the Converſion of Souls, the Work is done by his own Almighty Power.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT hath been ſhewn that the Lord in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting Souls</hi> doth uſually make uſe of <hi>Outward Means,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word.</hi> Now let us enquire more fully how thoſe that were <hi>ſpiritually dead,</hi> come to be <hi>made alive,</hi> and thoſe that were <hi>darkneſs, come to be made light in the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe that think man hath ſuch a <hi>principle</hi> and <hi>ſeed of Grace</hi> lying hid in his heart by <hi>nature,</hi> which if it be drawn forth by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:192261:52"/>and exhortations, and man will make uſe thereof, is ſufficient to <hi>convert</hi> him; do not enough conſider how utterly corrupted every man is by <hi>the Fall</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and without any <hi>ſpiritual ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, men are reproved in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for <hi>loving darkneſs rather then light;</hi> and becauſe <hi>they will not come to Chriſt that they may have life:</hi> But ſuch Scriptures are ſo far from implying, that we are able to change our own hearts, wills and affections: that they ſhew the (to us) invincible pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and oppoſition that is in our hearts to the Lord, that we have neither power nor will to turn unto him: ſuch ſayings of the holy Scripture do ſhew what need we have of the exceeding <hi>greatneſs of Gods power</hi> to work upon ſuch not onely impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent but wilful and deſperate Creatures as all are by nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There is indeed a certain kind of willing and running, and ſtriving in natural men upon great Convictions;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Balaam</hi> had, when he ſaid, <hi>Let me die the death of the righteous, and let my laſt end be like his.</hi> But this one Conſideration will be of much uſe to guide us in this queſtion, <hi>That when God commands men in his word to pray, to repent, and to believe in Chriſt;</hi> the meaning is,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:192261:53"/>
                  <hi>that they do theſe things from a principle of grace and ſpiritual life, that God only can work in us, and which we are to look to him for.</hi> All the ſuddain flaſhes of <hi>ſeeming re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> and <hi>prizing of Chriſt</hi> that come not from a <hi>principle of grace infuſed by the Spirit of God into the heart,</hi> but are the <hi>meer ſtruglings of an awakened Conſcience, to get from under the wrath of God,</hi> will bring no man to Heaven; neither do theſe <hi>workings of the heart</hi> anſwer to thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God, to <hi>believe,</hi> and to <hi>repent,</hi> but are only a ſhew of thoſe <hi>Graces:</hi> they are ſomething like <hi>Converſion,</hi> but are not <hi>Converſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This which hath been ſaid, may be Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated from the Parable of the <hi>ſtony ground,</hi> Matth. 13. to which they are compared <hi>that hear the word with joy, and for a time believe, and after fall away:</hi> this was only ſome ſuddain flaſh from the <hi>natural work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the heart upon the hearing of the word,</hi> accompanied with ſome <hi>common convictions,</hi> and <hi>common workings of the Spirit:</hi> But the Text ſaith, <hi>they had no root,</hi> they had not the <hi>root and habit of grace in their Souls, planted in them by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> from whence theſe things did proceed.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall ſay, <hi>How ſhall we know theſe
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:192261:53"/>ſudden workings of the heart, and flaſhes of ſeeming Converſion that ariſe but from natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſcience awakened and ſtartled with common convictions of the Spirit; as in</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam, Herod, Felix, <hi>and ſuch as are deſcribed in the Parable of the fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, from that believing, repenting, and thoſe ſpiritual affections that flow from the habit and principle of grace put into the Soul by the Spirit of God.</hi> I anſwer, <hi>That the difference may be known by the permanency and continuance.</hi> Such ſudden flaſhes as were in <hi>Balaam</hi> are ſoon over, and leave the heart unmortified, unpurged: But the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of grace in the hearts of <hi>Believers</hi> is <hi>eternal</hi> and <hi>remains for ever;</hi> where there is the root of grace in the heart, though it be not always putting forth it ſelf, yet there is a fixed principle and deſire in the heart to admire <hi>free grace,</hi> to <hi>prize Chriſt,</hi> and to <hi>cleave to Chriſt,</hi> to <hi>mourn for ſin,</hi> and to <hi>walk with God,</hi> though there is not always the ſame vigour and activity of <hi>grace</hi> in ſuch, yet there is a fixed bent and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deſire of the heart towards the Lord, which no time can wear off, which no temptations and oppoſition can wholly quench and extinguiſh.</p>
               <p>But to come nearer to this Point, to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:192261:54"/>make it moſt manifeſt, that <hi>Converſion</hi> is wrought by the <hi>meer grace and power of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Many that have the greateſt outward means of grace are never converted:</hi> Though they have godly Parents which inſtruct them diligently, and live under excellent preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and have met with many ſtartling Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences and great afflictions, yet they are never brought home to God; when as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that have carnal Parents that ſet them very bad examples, and have been brought up in ignorant and profane places and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and have lived where there hath been very poor and dark preaching, are ſometimes converted: this ſhews that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> is wrought by the <hi>meer grace and power of God.</hi> It may be ſome godly Parents after many and many prayers for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and great care to inſtruct them in the ways of God, have ſo little fruit of all, that thev count it a great matter if their poor Children have a little Civility and common Morality; it may be they have not that, but are profane <hi>Eſaus,</hi> and rebellious <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoloms,</hi> when as others that have had wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Parents that prejudiced them what they could againſt Religion from their Infancy, and when they began to look after Chriſt,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:192261:54"/>have oppoſed them with great rigour, threatning to turn them out of doors, and never own them, or do any thing for them if they follow Religion; yet they are turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Lord, and cannot be beaten off from his ways: this ſhews that it is the great and invincible <hi>power of God that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in them that believe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Some at the ſame time when the Lord began to convince them and convert them, have been going on as desperately and reſolutely in their ſins as ever they were all their days.</hi> As <hi>Paul</hi> was going to <hi>Damaſcus</hi> to make ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vock of the Saints, being (as himſelf after confeſſed) <hi>mad and outragious againſt the Church of God,</hi> yet then, and in that Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney <hi>the Lord converted him,</hi> Acts, 9. was not this the <hi>meer grace and power of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some have gone to hear godly Miniſters on purpoſe to ſcoff at them, or bring them into trouble,, and yet have been <hi>Converted</hi> at the hearing of them, finding a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous working of the Spirit of God upon their hearts, which was very ſtrange to them, and filled them with aſtoniſhment at the <hi>free grace and power of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some ignorant and carnal people, who at the beginning of a Sermon have ſlighted and deſpiſed it and the Preacher in their
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:192261:55"/>hearts, and have been filled with indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet by and by before the Sermon hath been ended, ſomething hath been ſet home upon their hearts, that hath convinced them of their miſerable eſtate, and brought them to Chriſt for help and ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Some at the ſame time when they were <hi>converted,</hi> have been more indiſpoſed and unwilling to hear the word, then at other times, but were even as it were hurried and thruſt upon the Ordinance that they knew not how, and when they have come there, have been more drowſie, ſleepy, and unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to hear the word then they uſed to be; when lo on a ſudden the Lord awakens and ſtartles their Conſciences by the Miniſtry of the Word, as if he himſelf had ſpoken immediately from Heaven to them by name, and ſo the Lord hath made that unlikely time the time of love, and the <hi>Day of his power to their Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes when Miniſters have been ſtraightned in their affections and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in Preaching, more then they have uſed to be, that they have gone on hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily in the work, and haver reflected upon their ſervice with much humiliation to their own Spirits, yet God hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times done much by ſuch weak means,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:192261:55"/>and converted ſome effectually at that time, that there hath been more good done at that time, then at many other times, (ſo far as comes to their knowledge) when they have been much aſſiſted in the work. God knows how his faithful Servants would preach and ſet forth his truth, and he is pleaſed to enlarge things by the inward light of his Spirit upon the minds of the hearers. ſometimes above what they did ſufficiently clear to them. All theſe Obſervations run into this, that God worketh all in all, he is the Author and Finiſher of our Faith, and that Miniſters can do no good, nor People that hear them receive any good, but as it is given from above, and when he will work nothing ſhall let it, not the ignorant indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſedneſs and prejudice of the hearers, nor the defects and weakneſs of his Servants that ſpeak in his Name.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Some of the worſt natural tempers, not onely of the weakeſt parts, but of moſt froward and croſs Spirits, are wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the grace of God; and men of ripe wits, and of more affable and courteous natures are never converted unto God.</hi> Thoſe differences among men that ariſe from their conſtitutions of body, whether it be for the better or the worſe, alter
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:192261:56"/>not the caſe, <hi>God hath mercy on whom he will have mercy;</hi> God can convert thoſe who are of the worſt natural tempers, and without he infuſe grace, thoſe who are of the ſweeteſt natural diſpoſitions, will never turn unto the Lord; yea the compoſedneſs of their natural temper may turn much to their prejudice, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them think they are in a good eſtate, becauſe they do not break out into ſuch paſſions and intemperances that others are very Subject to, although they know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of any <hi>New birth and ſanctifying work of the ſpirit upon their ſouls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Some very diſſolute and prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are converted, and many others that are free from ſuch groſs vice are never born again: Publicans, and Harlots, and ſuch as the theif upon the Croſs, are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times brought</hi> to a ſight of their ſins and to repent and believe in Chriſt, when others that never were ſo vile, go on quietly, reſting in their <hi>formality</hi> and <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,</hi> and never ſee their <hi>need of Christ</hi> and a <hi>work of grace upon their hearts,</hi> and ſo periſh for ever.</p>
               <p>When God doth convert men that have been <hi>notorious Sinners</hi> filled with <hi>all unrighteouſneſs,</hi> drunkards, ſwearers,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:192261:56"/>ſcoffers at <hi>Religion</hi> and old in ſin, too habituated and accuſtomed to all kind of evil, he proclames unto us, <hi>that the power of converting ſouls is of God and not of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, it doth require the <hi>exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatneſs of Gods power</hi> to convince a <hi>proud Phariſee,</hi> that truſteth in himſelf that <hi>he is righteous</hi> and deſpiſeth the <hi>righteouſneſs of Christ;</hi> that he is <hi>in the gall of bitterneſs and bonds of iniquity</hi> and to bring him as a poor, loſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done Sinner to ſeek for life from Chriſt, and in ſome reſpects ſuch have greater difficulties to be carried thorough to Chriſt then others; yet in regard that ſome of the other ſort are ſo outragious in ſin, and almoſt down right <hi>Atheiſts</hi> that make a mock and jear of all <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> and regard of <hi>God and the world to come,</hi> if the Lord pleaſe to convert ſuch (as ſometimes he doth) the <hi>exceeding greatneſs of Gods power ſhines forth moſt eminently therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the paſſages of mens <hi>Converſion</hi> ſhall be known in the <hi>world to come,</hi> it will be matter of <hi>everlaſting wonderment and aſtoniſhment to Angels and men,</hi> for then it will appear that God is to be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:192261:57"/>
                  <hi>admired for his free grace,</hi> and the <hi>exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing greatneſs of his power to all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, that I may ſtand no longer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this <hi>Point,</hi> let us conſider a few pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture more, that beyond all contradiction to eſtabliſh this truth, <hi>that converſion is wrought in the ſoul of man by the power of God alone.</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>the exceeding greatneſs of his power worketh towards them that believe,</hi> and <hi>that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his mighty power which wrought in Chriſt when he raiſed him from the dead,</hi> Epheſ. 1.19, 20. <hi>He that hath wrought us to the ſelf ſame thing is God,</hi> 2 Corin. 5.5. Hence it is a very proper ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion that wee commonly uſe when we ſpeak of <hi>mens converſion,</hi> to ſay, <hi>they were wrought upon at ſuch a time;</hi> for indeed except God had wrought them by the <hi>exceeding greatneſs of his power</hi> to this ſelf ſame thing, they had never turned from <hi>Sin</hi> to <hi>Chriſt. A new heart alſo will I give you and a new ſpirit will I put within you, I will take away the heart of ſtone and give you an heart of fleſh,</hi> Ezek. 36.26, 27.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Converſion</hi> the <hi>habit of grace</hi> is ſecretly infuſed into the heart, as life into a dead man; the ſoul is paſſive at firſt: hence it
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:192261:57"/>is ſaid of God in reference unto this work <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.18. <hi>That of his own will begat he us. [of his own will]</hi> that ſhews it is of his <hi>own meer grace</hi> and when it is ſaid <hi>[he begat us]</hi> that ſhews that it is of his <hi>own power,</hi> and that the Soul is firſt paſſive in the work. When a Soul is <hi>converted,</hi> it doth repent and doth act ſaith on Chriſt, and is active in a way of Grace, but firſt the Lord begets us ſpiritually, and in uſes ſpiritual life.</p>
               <p>We muſt not imagine that the ſoul never acts at all firſt or laſt, and that there are no created <hi>habits of grace;</hi> but firſt, the Lord infuſes the <hi>habit of Grace</hi> wherein the Soul is paſſive, and the Soul being changed and ſanctifyed thereby through the help and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the ſpirit, exciting and aſſiſting that <hi>New ſpiritual Life</hi> put into us, we are enabled to put forth acts of <hi>Faith, Repentance</hi> and other <hi>Graces.</hi> Firſt the Lord puts <hi>ſpiritual Life</hi> into us, and then in him (through his concurrence and ſecret aſſiſtance) we move and act <hi>ſpiritually</hi> and <hi>graciouſly.</hi> The ſumme of all is this, <hi>God firſt giveth repentance, and then we repent, God firſt giveth faith, and then we believe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All thoſe Scriptures were it is ſaid, <hi>that God giveth repentance, and giveth Faith,</hi> and <hi>worketh in us to will and to do,</hi> might all be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:192261:58"/>inſiſted on for further confirmation of this truth, <hi>That converſion is wrought by the power of God alone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe all thoſe Scriptures that ſet forth the weakneſs of the Saints, even after they are in the <hi>ſtate of grace,</hi> how they yet cry out to be <hi>delivered from the body of death,</hi> what need they have of <hi>aſſiſting grace, of new influences of the Spirit,</hi> and to be kept and upheld by the <hi>power of God</hi> unto the end of their dayes, and their continual prayers and Supplications to God ſtill to teach them, quicken them, enlarge their hearts, incline their hearts unto his <hi>Teſtimonies,</hi> and make them to go in the <hi>path of his Commandments</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> did in the Book of Pſalms) do ſhew, that we are both at firſt <hi>converted</hi> and afterwards carried on in Gods wayes, and kept and preſerved to the <hi>heavenly Kingdom by the power of God alone, to whom be glory for ever and ever; Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:192261:58"/>
            <head>Some are Converted young.</head>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Shewing that God Converts men at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Ages, ſome in Youth, ſome in their latter time, as it pleaſeth him.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw if we enquire into the times and ſeaſons when God hath <hi>Converted</hi> thoſe whom he hath <hi>Predeſtinated</hi> unto Life, there is great variety, according to the <hi>Counſel of his Will,</hi> there is a ſet time for the <hi>new and ſpiritual birth of the Elect,</hi> as well as there is <hi>an appointed time for every ones firſt birth and coming into the World.</hi> The ſelf ſame day and hour and moment that God hath <hi>d creed from Eternity,</hi> ſhall all the <hi>Elect of God</hi> be brought out of the <hi>Egypt</hi> of their <hi>natural condition,</hi> to travel towards the <hi>heavenly Canaan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore paſſing by what might be ſaid of Gods <hi>infuſing grace</hi> into ſome in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:192261:59"/>as he doth in <hi>Elect Infants</hi> that die in their Infancy, although the manner of his working grace in them, is a great ſecret to us; I ſhall only ſpeak of the times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Gods working grace in them that live ſome conſiderable time in the world.</p>
               <p>Firſt then I ſay, that God <hi>converts ſome in their youth,</hi> yea very young; this we know by Scripture and Experience, <hi>Joſiah, Oba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah,</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> are recorded in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for early Converts. All ſhould <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their Creator in the days of their youth:</hi> and ſome God helps by his grace ſo to do. It is a happy thing when in this ſenſe <hi>young ones firſt ſeek the Kingdom of God,</hi> before they ſeek after <hi>Wealth</hi> or <hi>Wife,</hi> or are ſcarce capable of regarding ſuch worldly matters. It is infinite mercy to be converted at all, and a great priviledge to be converted young.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Thoſe that are converted very young, uſually have not ſuch terrours and frights of Conſcience as others have in their Converſion,</hi> ſuch thundrings and earthquakes of <hi>Law terrours,</hi> but God ſpeaketh to them with a ſtiller voice, and deals more gently with them.</p>
               <p>Indeed ſuch are ſometimes ſorely tempted to queſtion the truth of their <hi>Converſion,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:192261:59"/>they have not had ſuch great <hi>terrors of conſcience</hi> as ſome others have had, which they have heard or read of, yet there is no ground for it: for as if a man hath had as great <hi>conſternation of Spirit and terrours of conſcience</hi> as ever <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> had, this were not ſufficient to prove that he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted: So if a man hath had little feeling of <hi>thoſe terrors,</hi> and yet can find that he loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes himſelf for ſin, prizes Chriſt, believes on his Name, and heartily deſires that he ſhould reigne over him, his eſtate is as good and ſafe for eternity, as if he had been twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years under <hi>extream horrour of conſcience</hi> night and day, and afterwards found <hi>peace in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly. <hi>Thoſe that are converted very young, uſually are prevented by the grace of God from committing many groſſe ſins which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are guilty of, as drunkenneſs,</hi> whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſcoffing at religion, and ſwearing, (though the two laſt of theſe ſins now a daies are riſe amongſt ſome that are very young, even to amazement) uſually Youth is not ſo debauched, I mean, the beginning of Youth as afterwards; ſo that if God pleaſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert one before he hath run into that exceſſe of riot, it is to be for ever remembred with thankfulneſs unto the Lord. If our ſouls ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:192261:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:192261:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:192261:61"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:192261:61"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:192261:62"/>came (in act) into ſome ſecret and open wickedneſs, which naturall men in proceſſe of time as they grow in years do commonly fall into, but that the Lord before our vile nature was ripe for the commiſſion of thoſe ſins, was pleaſed to <hi>Sanctify us</hi> and put his <hi>fear into our hearts</hi> that wee know not what many of thoſe things mean, but by heare-ſay and report we are to take it as a great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Yet by reaſon of this, ſome that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted young are apt to fall into <hi>temptation</hi> and <hi>a ſnare,</hi> being apt to be ever and anon leaning ſomething to their <hi>own righteouſneſs;</hi> But as God taketh them off by his <hi>grace</hi> from putting any confidence therein, and leadeth them forth again by his <hi>holy ſpirit</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all their blameleſs walking before or ſince their converſion, but dung in point of <hi>juſtification,</hi> and to the end of their days, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all their doing and ſuffering, deſiring onely to be <hi>found in Chriſt,</hi> having on them <hi>his righteouſneſs</hi> to juſtifie them at <hi>Gods Bar.</hi> And herein lies much of the light and leading of the ſpirit of God in them that are true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, that although others that are ignorant of theſe things, may think that they have not much need of the <hi>righteouſneſs of Chriſt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not been ſtained with groſſe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:192261:62"/>ſins all their dayes, (and they themſelves at times may be tempted to ſuch thoughts) yet the Lord ſhews them that they are ſo vile by <hi>nature,</hi> and their <hi>beſt righteouſneſs</hi> ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, that they have as much need to prize Chriſt, and to live purely and folely upon <hi>his righteouſneſs,</hi> as any poor creatures in the world.</p>
               <p>Again, thoſe that are <hi>converted young,</hi> and have not committed ſome <hi>groſs ſins,</hi> that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have committed, are apt to carry it not with that compaſſion of the ignorant, and of them that are out of the way, and utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly debauched, as thoſe many times do who have run to the ſame <hi>exceſſe of riot</hi> and are now <hi>converted unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas that is the right Spirit of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to be <hi>very pitiful,</hi> yea very gentle in our carriage to the vileſt of man, yet rightly tempered with a holy zeal againſt ſin.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe thoſe that are <hi>converted young,</hi> and have not committed ſuch <hi>abominations</hi> as others have done, are apt to be lifted up with a conceit of their own ſtrength, and not to be ſo ſenſible of the <hi>corruption of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> as others are; wherefore the Lord doth ſometimes leave them unto <hi>great temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> and ſometimes to fall fouly in ſome
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:192261:63"/>things for a ſeaſon (even after their <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi>) that they may ſee what is in their hearts, and that they ſhould have been as <hi>vile as any in the World,</hi> if the Lord had not beſtowed his <hi>grace upon them:</hi> Whereupon the come to have <hi>great humiliation</hi> before the Lord, and loath themſelves in his ſight. And if God do keep ſome that are <hi>converted young</hi> from being tainted with <hi>groſs ſins,</hi> firſt or laſt all their dayes, yet ſometimes they may be ſo near the Commiſſion of them (but that God doth graciouſly prevent, either by ſome <hi>ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Providence,</hi> or by filling their heart on a ſudden with the <hi>bleſſed Motions of his Spirit,</hi> whereby the <hi>ſnare is broken,</hi> and <hi>they eſcape</hi>) that the remembrance thereof is enough to keep them humble all their dayes. Beſides, if it have not been ſo with ſuch that they have not been <hi>almoſt</hi> in ſuch evils, <hi>almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded and enticed to ſuch groſs ſins,</hi> yet there is the <hi>Sin of our natures,</hi> and the ſins of <hi>daily infirmity,</hi> diſtractions in holy duties, <hi>vaine thoughts, ſinful paſſions, idle words,</hi> and the like; for which we have cauſe to lie in the duſt before God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly. <hi>Thoſe that are converted young do many times attain to a higher degree of grace before they die, then others who are converted in their latter time,</hi> eſpecially thoſe that are
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:192261:63"/>
                  <hi>converted young,</hi> and live long afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they finiſh their courſe, ſuch have longer time to <hi>grow in grace and in</hi> the <hi>knowledge of our Lord and ſaſiour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet that none that were <hi>converted young,</hi> may be <hi>high-minded but feare,</hi> let it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that it is not alwayes thus, but ſome of theſe through <hi>great temptations,</hi> and falls into ſin, are but weak in grace all their days; and ſome that were converted many years after them do get the ſtart of them in <hi>grace,</hi> are more awful of God, more weaned from the world, and more fruitful in their courſe.</p>
               <p>And greatly are ſome humbled when they count the number of the years ſince God firſt wrought upon them, and think with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves how little <hi>communion</hi> they have with God, how little <hi>mortification</hi> to the world, how little <hi>ſervice</hi> they have done for God, and then look upon others that have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted many years after them, and ſee to what a greater meaſure of grace they have attained. Though they do not envy the <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of God to ſuch, but rejoyce therein, and give thanks unto his Name for his grace beſtowed on them, yet they reflect upon themſelves, as thoſe who have quenched and grieved the <hi>holy Spirit of God,</hi> for which he
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:192261:64"/>is not pleaſed (they think) to influence and quicken and comfort them, as he doth others, that have been more obedient, and ſo their ſouls are greatly abaſed before the Lord.</p>
               <p>Of theſe things which have been ſpoken of <hi>converſion in youth,</hi> this is the ſumme, That it is in it ſelf a <hi>great priviledge;</hi> and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs ſuch as are <hi>converted young,</hi> had need to <hi>watch and pray, be very humble and diligent leaſt they fall into temptations and ſnares, and go on very ſlowly and heavily in the wayes of God.</hi> Likewiſe from what hath been ſaid, it doth appeare, that how ever wee may be advantaged in ſome <hi>circumſtances</hi> and <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges</hi> above others, as in being in Chriſt before them, and the like; yet without <hi>great ſupplies of grace</hi> from above, we ſhall not make a <hi>proficiency</hi> according to ſuch <hi>advantages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I leave this head it may be profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeak ſome thing more, by way of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and counſel to thoſe that are converted young.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Have a care of errours of Judgement,</hi> Youth is uſually <hi>raw</hi> and <hi>ignorant;</hi> you may have ſtrong and good affections, but it may be weak judgments; go not out of <hi>novelty</hi> to hear <hi>unſound Preachers,</hi> give your ſelves to <hi>Prayer</hi> and to the reading of the <hi>Word</hi>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:192261:64"/>attend upon the <hi>Faithful Preaching of the word by the Miniſters of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Be much in proving your own ſelves whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have a ſound work of grace upon your hearts,</hi> the end of it uſually to them that are ſincere is a ſuller aſſurance that they are <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from Death to Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Flie youthfull luſts,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> exhorted <hi>Timothy.</hi> (2 Epiſt. 2.22.) one that was <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted young,</hi> and was yet but a young man, when the Apoſtle wrote thus unto him; flee <hi>pride,</hi> flee all kinds of <hi>uncleaneſs,</hi> flee <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful recreations,</hi> flee <hi>bad company</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>Have a care that through ignorance you do not commit ſome ſins in your youth that may wound your conſciences much in age: In ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per years you may ſee ſome things to be ſin, which you would not have done in your youth if you had known ſo much then. Therefore ſtudy the <hi>Scriptures</hi> well and beg of God to ſhew you what ſins youth uſeth to fall into, &amp; knows it not then, but it may be afterward to the great wounding of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat the Lord that while you are yet young men or Women you may <hi>cleanſe your way, and take heed thereunto according to his word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Often bleſs the name of the Lord for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing himſelf to you ſo ſoon in your young and tender years,</hi> Wonder at the Lords <hi>free
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:192261:65"/>grace</hi> that he ſhould convert you at all, and labour to be much affected with the time when he did it in the <hi>morning of your lives,</hi> ſo <hi>ſoon,</hi> ſo <hi>early.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Whatſoever difficulties, temptations, and afflictions you go thorough in the courſe of your pilgrimage, let your hearts truſt ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Lord, that his grace ſhall be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for you: He will never leave you nor forſake you;</hi> ſo that you may boldly ſay, <hi>the Lord is your helper,</hi> what ever ſad lots of affliction are upon you; and <hi>that all things ſhall work together for your good.</hi> If God hath been the <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Guide</hi> of your <hi>youth,</hi> he will be the God of your <hi>riper years,</hi> and though in your latter time you may have great decaies of body, and can do him little ſervice, yet he will be tender of you and care for you, and do you good to gray hairs, and in gray hairs, he will bear you, and he will carry you in his <hi>everlasting Arms</hi> to <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may have many <hi>a Thorne in the fleſh,</hi> many <hi>humbling temptations,</hi> leaſt you ſhould be lifted up, but be not diſmayed, for the Lord is your God, and he will ſtrengthen you, he will help you, he will uphold you with the <hi>right hand of his righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Admire him that is of power to keep you, and hath kept you, and will keep you in the ſtate
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:192261:65"/>of grace unto the end:</hi> remember the former dayes when you were firſt illuminated, what <hi>difficulties</hi> the Lord carried you through, how he made you able, by the <hi>power of his grace,</hi> to break off from evil company, and from your ſinful courſes, and it may be to endure a great <hi>fight</hi> of <hi>afflictions</hi> from carnal Parents, and Relations, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance; and though you were young, youthfull, and very unconſtant, yet by the power of God, you were not afraid of any amazement, and could not be turned aſide from following the Lord.</p>
               <p>Some that are <hi>converted young</hi> are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtrengthned with ſuch might by the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> that though they have carnal Parents and Relations, that oppoſe them in the wayes of God, they carry it with that <hi>Patience, humbleneſs of mind</hi> and yet with that <hi>magnanimity and courage,</hi> that is to be wondered at; even while they are young and but Children, they may go through ſuch <hi>difficulties</hi> with a holy rejoycing, as would be hard for them to go through af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards without very much aſſiſting grace from God.</p>
               <p>Remember therefore and forget not the <hi>kindneſs of the Lord</hi> to you in your youth, and how he hath yet maintained the <hi>work of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:192261:66"/>grace</hi> in you, keeping <hi>grace alive</hi> through ſo long a tract of time, as ſome of you have <hi>walked with God,</hi> who were <hi>converted young.</hi> And though your <hi>hearts and lives</hi> are not ſo with God as you would have it, and that you have not yet ſo far attained as to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but ſtill groan and ſigh being burdened with your <hi>corruptions and temptations;</hi> yet thank and praiſe the Lord that hath taught you from your <hi>youth up,</hi> and that hitherto he hath kept you in that great and terrible wilderneſs you have gone thorough, and that his ſpirit and his feare is yet you.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Have a care of abating in your firſt love and zeal and ſincerity and diligence in following the Lord.</hi> Let the ſpiritual dew of your youth be alwaies upon you, that you may be alwaies green and flouriſhing in grace, that as your dayes ſo may your <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual strength</hi> be. Give not the men of the World occaſion to ſay, <hi>that your forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in religion in your youth was becauſe you wanted wit then,</hi> but that now you are grown wiſer, you follow the World as hard as others, take liberty in your converſation as others do, and give over preciſeneſs and ſtrict walking; but let them ſee that now your judgments are bettered with <hi>age</hi> and much <hi>experience</hi> you ſtill chuſe rather <hi>to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:192261:66"/>ſuffer affliction with the People of God then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin that are but for a ſeaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>it is very requiſite for thoſe that are converted young and are but yet young to read the Scriptures diligently concerning the duties that God requireth of men in thoſe Relations that his Providence hath put them into, or ſhall put them into in the world.</hi> Study well the duties of Servants and Maſters, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Parents, Wives and Husbands, and other Relations. As the beſt Saints are apt to miſcarry much in their duties in the Relations they ſtand in, ſo eſpecially thoſe that are <hi>young,</hi> for want of knowledge of what God requires in his <hi>Word</hi> in thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. Therefore art thou called being very young? ſtudy upon thoſe duties that the <hi>Scripture</hi> requires towards thy <hi>Parents</hi> (if they be yet alive) and make great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of them. Art thou called being a <hi>Servant,</hi> or intended to be ſo ſhortly read over thoſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> that ſpeak of the <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Servants</hi> again and again, pray over thoſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> often, that <hi>God would make thee obedient, diligent,</hi> and <hi>faithful</hi> in that <hi>Relation</hi> as his <hi>Word</hi> requires. Art thou <hi>called,</hi> and art ſoon to <hi>marry,</hi> or art newly <hi>married?</hi> ſtudy thoſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:192261:67"/>that <hi>eſtate:</hi> and ſo for Maſters and Parents, and the like. The <hi>holy Scriptures</hi> are able to teach you your duties in all theſe things, that you may be throughly ſurniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with directions from them.</p>
               <p>Let no young people deſpiſe this counſel, for through their not giving attendance to the Reading &amp; ſtudy of <hi>the Scripture</hi> in theſe things, they many times offend God much, and whatſoever <hi>grace</hi> they have, the <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>luſtre</hi> of it is exceedingly darkned before the eyes of men. We hear of ſuch a young perſon that is much affected with the <hi>word</hi> and <hi>prayes</hi> much, ſpeaks of good things, and prizes Chriſt: but when we inquire how doth he carry it to his Parents or his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or to his Yoak-fellow, it is oftentimes a grief of mind to the Godly-wiſe, and makes them they know not what to think, there is ſo great failing in thoſe duties.</p>
               <p>Now I am ſpeaking of the Lords con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting ſome very young. Note this, that ſometimes young people, and eſpecially thoſe that have good education live in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Families, and under the faithful preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word, are much convinced and ſet upon <hi>prayer,</hi> and others rejoyce and hope that it will be a <hi>through work;</hi> and yet all this comes to nothing, they ſoon loſe
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:192261:67"/>all ſenſe of thoſe things, and grow more vile in their practiſes then they were before. And others of them to pleaſe their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are godly, after they have loſt the power of thoſe <hi>common convictions</hi> they have had, will ſeem to be religious ſtill for a while, but when their godly Parents are dead, or they come to leave good Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and be for themſelves, then they will ſhew what they are indeed. Some are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Hypocrites very young, and having good parts, and finding that the profeſſion of Religion makes them acceptable to ſome upon whom they have dependance, will make a fair ſhew to deceive others; but let them know, that they deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt in the end when they come to have their portion with the <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> where there is <hi>weeping and wailing and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have dwelt long enough upon this firſt Head, to ſhew that God doth convert ſome in youth, yea very young, and have given cautions and counſel unto ſuch. Now to proceed:</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>God doth convert ſome in their riper years, in the midſt of their days, or in old age, as it pleaſeth him.</hi> Abraham in the Old Teſtament, and <hi>Nicodemus</hi> in the New,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:192261:68"/>are recorded as perſons converted in their riper years and latter time; but whereas ſome ſay, ſhew any other inſtances beſides them of perſons converted in their latter time? I will ſay that we know not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe age of the three thouſand that were converted, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. nor of thoſe <hi>Acts</hi> 4.5. nor of thoſe Multitudes that were <hi>added to the Lord,</hi> Acts 5.14. nor of <hi>Cornelius his friends,</hi> Acts 10. <hi>upon whom the Holy Ghoſt fell,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we know the preciſe age of <hi>Lydia,</hi> the Jaylor, and many others that are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by name in the Scripture, whether they were young or old when they were converted, nor is it neceſſary for us to know it: It is ſufficient for us to know, <hi>that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever cometh unto Chriſt, he will in no wiſe caſt out, whether he be young or old.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe holy men that ſhew what an unſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able time old age is, to have then the work to do, to <hi>make our calling and election ſure,</hi> when we can ſcarce ſee to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, can ſcarce hear the <hi>word of life</hi> that is preached to them, and their Memories and parts extreamly decayed, muſt not be underſtood, as if God could not convert ſuch, or never did it, but to ſhew that the repentance of ſuch is very often feigned and counterfeit, and to warn young people that
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:192261:68"/>they do not count upon old-age converſion to the neglecting of <hi>remembring their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour in the days of their youth.</hi> It is a great truth that they ſay, that God ſhould not be put off to take the dregs of our lives, and to take the Devils leavings, for he deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the beginning of our ſtrength, the beſt of our days, and all our days to ſerve him, but better late then never, better come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Vineyard at the eleventh hour then not at all. There have been remarkable converſions of old men recorded by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men, O that there were more both young and old brought home to Chriſt. I know none that will forbid the oldeſt Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to come to Chriſt: If they do not flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God with their lips, and feign themſelves to be Saints, but are indeed born again, though they be old, they ſhall enter into the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <p>It is true, elder perſons that are uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted are more habituated to ſin, and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually more prejudiced againſt the power of Religion then thoſe that are younger, but they have more ſins to humble them, and ſhew them their need of Chriſt, if the Lord pleaſe to give them a ſight and ſenſe of them. God is pleaſed to convert ſome that were the moſt unlikely to find mercy every way,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:192261:69"/>very ignorant, very profane, and now wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en old alſo; who would have ſaid or thought that ſuch ſhould ever have turned to the Lord? But is any thing too hard for God? <hi>wonders of grace</hi> are the <hi>greateſt wonders</hi> that God doth, and will be the moſt admired to Eternity.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall enquire further concerning theſe things, and ask whether God doth convert any now a-days towards the very end of their lives upon their Death-beds, or in a dying hour?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, that although none ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume upon this, and think there is time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough yet to repent and turn to God: yet ſurely that famous inſtance of the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Thief upon the Croſs in a dying-hour, is recorded for an encouragement of all ſuch as hereafter come to be ſenſible of their ſins, though very late, that they ſhould not ſay, <hi>there is no hope,</hi> and that therefore they will not have a thought of looking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pardon in Chriſt, but that they may ſee that (for ought they know, there is a may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be of <hi>mercy</hi> yet.</p>
               <p>We muſt not ſay that <hi>converſion</hi> was never wrought in any in a dying-hour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this Thief upon the Croſs, 'tis not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary indeed for uſually as men live, ſo
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:192261:69"/>they die, thoſe that lived in groſs ignorance and profaneneſs uſually die ſo, even die like ſpiritual fools, without ſenſe of ſin, without making out after <hi>union with Chriſt,</hi> and without any ſerious conſideration of that <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of happineſs</hi> or <hi>miſery</hi> to which they are going: but God may work much upon ſome very near their deaths, that were very ignorant and vile before, that while men are on this ſide Hell, and the Gulf is not fixed between them and ſalvation (how vile ſo ever they have been all their days) let none take away all incouragement from them to repent and come to Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Indeed it is a difficult thing, and requires much of the wiſdom from above in a godly Miniſter or Chriſtian (who it may be now is ſent for to come and diſcourſe with, and pray with an ignorant, profane, ſick and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſon, that hated and ſcoffed all ſuch in times paſt when the thoughts of death were far from them) to know how to ſpeak to ſuch, ſo as neither to bolſter them up in their ignorance and carnal preſumption, nor to hide the Goſpel, and the <hi>way to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of refuge from them.</hi> One that duly weighs all things will find this a hard task indeed. Thoſe that being called to ſick and dying perſons can upon meer formalities at
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:192261:70"/>an adventure though they be never ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and wicked aſſure them that all is well, and that they have but a little bodily pain to grapple with, and ſo to go to Heaven, make eaſie work of it. But O for one that knows and conſiders that few are ſaved, and that <hi>except a man be born again he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God,</hi> and that underſtands that this ſick-dying-perſon hath been very ignorant, and hath lived without God in the world, to know how to ſpeak rightly; to ſuch requires much heavenly wiſdom. The <hi>viſitation of ſick and dying perſons</hi> is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many accounts a harder work to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form after a right manner then moſt are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of, and eſpecially if thoſe perſons be ignorant and profane that we are called to viſit. Very dangerous is the caſe of thoſe that are near a dying hour, and are yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted, there is but a ſtep between them and Hell,: O if they were ſenſible of it, what trembling would take hold of them? but if yet at laſt the Lord will work grace in them, and ſay they ſhall not go down to the <hi>Infernal Pit,</hi> (though they are ſo near it) I have found a <hi>ranſom,</hi> let none envy the <hi>grace of God</hi> to them. Let none from what hath been ſaid, take heart to go on in their ignorance and profaneneſs in their health
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:192261:70"/>and ſtrength, and think all may be well at laſt, what if now and then a Malefactour hath his Pardon come when he is upon the Ladder, and the Rope about his Neck, and he ready to be turned off, for one ſuch are not many ſcores executed and put to death. If it were but for the life of your body, you would be loath to truſt to that, but men are moſt careleſs of their Souls, and though there be a Pardon-Office ſet up in Chriſt, yet few look after it in their youth and health, and ſtrength, but think their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don will come ſoon enough to ſave them from Hell, it may do ſo, it is well if it do. But O bold ſinner, thou run'ſt a mighty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, what if this Pardon never come? What if God ſay, <hi>Take him Juſtice, take him Devils, take him Hell, I will ſhew him no mercy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:192261:71"/>
            <head>How we may know we are CONVERTED.</head>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of the way how we may know that we are Converted and paſſed from Death to Life.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen a Soul is truly <hi>Converted,</hi> then his <hi>ſtate</hi> is ſafe for <hi>Eternity.</hi> If one that is <hi>converted</hi> ſhould die preſently after (as did the penitent Thief upon the Croſs) he is as ſure to go to Heaven as if he had lived never ſo long to ſerve Chriſt, and to ſuffer for his Name in the world: for in the inſtant of our <hi>Converſion</hi> we receive <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by whom we are <hi>justified,</hi> and we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his <hi>Spirit</hi> which ſhall be in us for ever.</p>
               <p>But whether we are to die ſoon, or to abide many days in this world after our <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion,</hi> it is very deſirable to know this happy change that God hath made of our condition; for the more aſſurance we have that God hath called us into the <hi>fellowſhip of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> the more
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:192261:71"/>we ſhall love God, praiſe God, rejoyce in God; the more patient in <hi>afflictions,</hi> the more willing to bear the <hi>Croſs,</hi> the more deſirous to depart and to be with <hi>Chriſt:</hi> And in a word, the clearer our <hi>union with Chriſt is to us,</hi> the more ſweet and eaſie will all the <hi>duties of Religion be to us,</hi> and the more holy and fruitful ſhall we be in our whole courſe, and that from a principle of <hi>Gospel ingenuity and gratitude:</hi> We ſhall be the more conſtrained by the love of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to live to him, when we know and are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he hath died for us, and as a <hi>fruit of his death,</hi> hath drawn us unto himſelf. Thoſe that would have them that are in <hi>Christ,</hi> to be always in ſuſpenſe and ſtand in doubt of their <hi>eternal conditions,</hi> accounting it a piece of <hi>Chriſtian humility</hi> and <hi>holy modeſty</hi> ſo to do; yea, thinking ſuch a frame to be a great <hi>preſervative from ſin,</hi> and a <hi>spur to quicken them to more diligence in Gods ways,</hi> then if the <hi>aſſurance of the love of God were ſhed abroad in their hearts by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> do erre, not conſidering ſo fully the <hi>nature of Gospel Grace,</hi> and <hi>a lively hope of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that it doth <hi>ſtrengthen and enlarge the Soul in holineſs and obedience,</hi> by urging new and further motives to our <hi>walking with God and fruitfulneſs before him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:192261:72"/>
               <p>It is the duty of all to try their ſpiritual eſtates and not to reſt ſatisfied in ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of the <hi>truth and power of grace</hi> in them, but to give diligence to the attaining of a full aſſurance thereof.</p>
               <p>Wherefore are we called upon ſo often in the Scripture, <hi>to prove our own works, to examine our ſelves whether we be in the faith or no,</hi> to <hi>give diligence to make our calling and election ſure,</hi> if it be not that thoſe that are not yet <hi>converted</hi> may find it out, that they may not deceive themſelves, but now look after <hi>union with Chriſt,</hi> which yet they have not, and that thoſe that are <hi>converted</hi> indeed may be aſſured of it, and ſo rejoyce and give praiſe, and be ſtirred up <hi>to walk worthy in all things of the vocation wherewith they are called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a man be not yet truly <hi>converted unto God,</hi> it is better for him to know how his condition is, though for the preſent it fill his Soul with much <hi>anxiety</hi> and <hi>fear of the wrath to come,</hi> then that he ſhould go on quietly and preſumptuouſly to Hell. If we be <hi>fooliſh Virgins,</hi> without the <hi>Oyle of grace in our veſſels,</hi> 'tis better to know it now whilſt <hi>Oyl</hi> may be got, then not to know it till time is paſt, and the door is ſhut.</p>
               <p>Many are greatly offended when they
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:192261:72"/>are put upon trying their <hi>spiritual eſtates,</hi> they ſay, <hi>ſuch preaching troubles their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> they are loath to ſee in what a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition they are, but if the Lord delight in them to make them his people, they will bleſs God that ever they ſate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch an <hi>awakening Miniſtry</hi> by which the Lord brought them to ſee they were in the <hi>broad way that leadeth to deſtruction,</hi> and brought them out of it unto <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then in anſwer to this great Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>How may a man know that he is truly converted, and in the ſtate of grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>It may be known by diſcerning the work of grace upon the Heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>It may be known by the more immediate teſtimony of the spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Converſion may be known by diſcerning the work of grace upon the heart. If a man think himſelf ſomething when he is nothing, he deceiveth himſelf,</hi> Gal. 6.3. Well then how ſhall ſuch a man be undeceived? <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>Let every man prove his own work, ſo ſhall he have rejoycing in himſelf alone, and not in another.</hi> That is, let him try whether the Lord hath <hi>began the good work of grace in him,</hi> let him <hi>prove and examine himſelf, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath true faith, true repentance, true love to God, true love to the brethren, ſo ſhall
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:192261:73"/>he have rejoycing in himſelf alone, diſcerning that God hath wrought in him thoſe things that accompany ſalvation,</hi> and not rejoyce meerly in the good opinion of others, who though they be <hi>gracious</hi> and <hi>spiritual,</hi> may eaſily be deceived in judging of the <hi>ſpiritual eſtate</hi> of others, being not ſo ſuſpicious of others as they are of themſelves, and know not the <hi>ſecret paſſages</hi> between God and their Souls, as they know things between God and themſelves.</p>
               <p>Many Scriptures might be brought to ſhew that we are to take this courſe in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our <hi>spiritual eſtates. Hereby we know that we know him, if we keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> 1 John 2.3. <hi>Hereby know we that we are in him,</hi> v. 4. <hi>We know that we are paſſed from death to life becauſe we love the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> 1 John 3.14. Thoſe that deny <hi>inherent grace</hi> in thoſe that are <hi>converted,</hi> or would not have them to try their <hi>spiritual eſtates</hi> thereby, are much miſtaken.</p>
               <p>Let thoſe who would know whether they be yet <hi>converted,</hi> ſet themſelves as in the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord,</hi> and examine themſelves whether the Lord hath made them ſenſible of the danger and evil that there is in ſin? whether the Lord hath taken them off from truſting in their own righteouſneſs and ſtrength? whether the Lord hath revealed
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:192261:73"/>Chriſt to them as Mediator, and fixed their hearts to put their whole truſt in him, Whether the Lord hath <hi>wrought in them godly ſorrow for ſin,</hi> and put a <hi>new bent of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs upon their hearts,</hi> to deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to walk ſo as to pleaſe God.</p>
               <p>He that would have theſe things more fully opened, let him remember or look back to the Third Chapter, where I have ſhewn more largely <hi>what Converſion and Special Grace is,</hi> and to let him examine himſelf ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. But that I may <hi>(through the grace of Chriſt)</hi> be further helpful to thoſe who would try their <hi>ſpiritual eſtates,</hi> to find out what God hath done for their <hi>Souls,</hi> let theſe things be obſerved:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That the work of grace is not always alike viſible and diſcernable in a Child of God, neither to himſelf nor others with whom he hath to do. Through bodily diſtempers, through vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent temptations, through ſore falls into ſin, and great diſſertions and hidings of Gods face,</hi> (from none of which a Child of God is wholly exempted in this life) it may come to paſs that a true Saint may be very hard put to it to diſcern <hi>the work of grace</hi> in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yea very much fear that he hath no <hi>true grace,</hi> and walk in darkneſs and trouble of ſpirit thereupon: With ſome it is thus a great while, God orders it thus (amongſt
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:192261:74"/>other holy ends of his) by ſuch examples of troubled Conſciences, to put others upon more tryal of their <hi>spiritual eſtates,</hi> to draw forth our pity and compaſſion to ſuch as are in theſe <hi>spiritual diſtreſſes,</hi> and to make us more thankful for the <hi>light of Gods spirit,</hi> to diſcern the <hi>work of grace</hi> in ourſelves, which theſe poor ſorrowful ones cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto, and to ſhew us that which I am now upon, <hi>that grace being ſo little in the beſt,</hi> is ſometimes ſcarce diſcernable, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the body is ſickyl and diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, and there is ſome ſpecial <hi>hour</hi> and <hi>power of darkneſs upon us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the way, I am afraid that ſometimes <hi>godly Miniſters</hi> unawares may deliver ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things that may much puzzle poor <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> about trying <hi>the work of grace upon their hearts,</hi> and bring them into <hi>great darkneſs and trouble of spirit.</hi> However that which I ſhall take notice of may be a Caution to ſuch as ſhall read theſe things, that they do not ſo, I have obſerved that <hi>Ministers</hi> do ſometimes ſpeak ſo unwarily of the <hi>ſigns of this grace,</hi> and the other, that thoſe <hi>ſigns</hi> which they lay down, are <hi>ſigns</hi> only of the <hi>high actings of that grace,</hi> and are not to be brought in as <hi>tryals</hi> whether a perſon hath the truth of that grace which may be, and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:192261:74"/>yet not thoſe <hi>high actings</hi> of it. I affect plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and not obſcurity, therefore I would try to make out my obſervation better, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Miniſter is preaching about <hi>the nature of Faith,</hi> and ſhall make this a ſign to the people to <hi>try their Faith</hi> by, if they can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve at all times that God will bring about every particular thing for them, which their eyes are towards him, for and which he hath promiſed without <hi>heſitation,</hi> wavering and conſidering and poring upon thoſe things that ſtand in the way of the mercy; and for this quote <hi>Abrahams</hi> Example that <hi>when he had the promiſe of a Son</hi> in his old Age, <hi>he conſidered not his own body, nor yet the dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Sarahs womb,</hi> Rom. 4. 18. 19. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is ſaid there; <hi>that he being not weak</hi> in faith, <hi>but strong in faith,</hi> was enabled to do ſo. That ſuch things muſt be brought in as examples of what <hi>believers</hi> ſhould do, and of what <hi>believers</hi> are ſometimes enabled through the grace of God to do, even to act faith very highly and ſtrongly, and not to prove that he is not a <hi>true believer</hi> that doth not alwayes thus. And ſo if this be laid down as a tryal of Faith that one that hath <hi>true faith</hi> will not be daunted in the times of the greateſt peril nor uſe ſinful waies to bring himſelf out of trouble, and quote for
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:192261:75"/>this the Heroick courage of the three Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren before <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> Daniel 3. and <hi>Davids encouraging himſelf in the Name of the Lord</hi> when <hi>Ziklag</hi> was taken, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſpake of <hi>ſtoning him,</hi> 1 Sam. 30.6. How may this puzle poor ſouls, and make them reflect upon themſelves, as if they had no <hi>true faith</hi> becauſe it may be they have found many fears in time of danger, and uſed ſome ſinful ſhifting in time of trouble. Yea, and did not thoſe men who were ſo Famous in their gennerations Falter much in their Faith and courage ſometimes as <hi>Abraham</hi> when he twice denyed <hi>Sarah</hi> to be his Wife as wee ſee in <hi>Geneſes,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> when he denyed Chriſt, and yet ſtill the habit of Faith remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, and <hi>David</hi> though all that time before mentioned he was bold in his God yet all other times how fearful was he, and that preſently after God had emminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeared for him 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.1. and then he was ſore afraid of <hi>Achiſh</hi> King of <hi>Gath</hi> and changed his behaviour, and feigned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf mad and ſcrabled at the doors of the gate <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all to get out off the danger he was in. Therefore careful muſt we be when we ſet before others tryals of the grace of God in them, that we do not take Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that ſpeak of the ſaints of old when
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:192261:75"/>they acted grace highly, and urge this upon people that if they do not alwaies ſo they have not the <hi>truth of grace</hi> in them, Indeed ſuch examples of the Saints ſhould be inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on to ſhew others what they ſhould do in like caſes, but not to make them tryals of <hi>the truth of their grace,</hi> ſo as that they ſhould conclude they have not the <hi>truth of grace</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they are in every thing at all times aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted and influenced by the ſpirit of God, as they were ſometimes. <hi>Abraham David</hi> and <hi>Peter, ſometimes acted above themſelves</hi> thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh the ſtrong help of aſſiſting <hi>grace,</hi> and <hi>ſometimes acted as much below themſelves,</hi> thorough the power of temptations, and the remainder of corruption that was in them, and ſo it is with other Saints. He therefore that will not lay a ſtumbling block before the weak in ſpeaking of theſe things, muſt carefully diſtinguiſh between what a true Saint is in his principles, deſire and bent of his heart, in which he is holy and gracious (for the Law of God is in his heart) and what he is or may be in ſome particular acts in which he may diſcover many fallings: We muſt diſtinguiſh between what a Saint ſhould be, and would be, and what he is and attaineth to in this life, we muſt deſtingniſh between what a Saint is ſometimes when he
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:192261:76"/>is ſtrongly influenced and aſſiſted by the holy Ghoſt, and what he is at other times when the Lord leaves him (in part) for his humilation, and that he may ſee what is in his heart. We muſt diſtinguiſh between what a true Saint is in his maine courſe, ſo he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth with God, and what he is at ſometimes when as (Paul himſelf ſaith) the evil which he would not do, and that which he hates that he doth. The life of grace in the hearts of believers is a great myſtery, the fleſh op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the ſpirit, and the ſpirit the fleſh in them, the fleſh and corruption in them cannot precipitate them to evil, as it would, becauſe of the ſpirit and grace of <hi>God</hi> that oppoſeth it, and the grace and new Nature that is in a Saint, cannot do the good that it would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the fleſh that oppoſeth it.</p>
               <p>All that I aim at is, that as Miniſters doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine ſhould be quick and powerful to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince ignorant and preſumptuous Sinners, that they are in the way to deſtruction, ſo they ſhould be careful at the ſame time that they do not <hi>quench the ſmoaking flax nor break the bruiſed Reed,</hi> puzling and making ſad any righteous ones, whom God would not have made ſad, remembring that it is one end of the Miniſtry of the Goſpel that we ſhould be helpers of their joy; and ſo
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:192261:76"/>much for this digreſſion.</p>
               <p>Grace is not alwaies alike viſible in true believers as hath been ſhewn ſometimes, the Saints walk in the Sun-ſhine: and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the dark, therefore it is needful that we ſhould be often trying our ſpiritual eſtates and ſometimes ſet ſpecial times apart for ſelf examination, if happily we may find that God hath called us into the fellowſhip of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>In trying our ſpiritual eſtates by ſings of the work of grace upon our hearts, it is beſt or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily to try our ſelves about the main things wherein the work of grace doth principally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt:</hi> as to try whether we have <hi>true faith in Chriſt, true repentance, true love to God,</hi> and the like; or elſe, through our weakneſs we are apt to be confounded by a multitude of ſigns, this way is ſafe enough, for where there is only <hi>grace in truth</hi> there is all, at leaſt in the <hi>root</hi> and <hi>habit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>In trying and examining the work of grace upon our hearts, we muſt pray for the light of the ſpirit to ſhew us thoſe graces that he hath wrought in us, otherwiſe it will be hard to diſcern them. The Holy Ghoſt</hi> can put a Inſture and ſhine upon our <hi>graces,</hi> and when the Conſcience is in great diſtreſs, can ſay, <hi>be not afraid Chriſt is here,</hi> ſee <hi>thou believeſt
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:192261:77"/>in him, thou feareſt God,</hi> and loveſt him in ſincerity.</p>
               <p>When a <hi>believer</hi> is examining the <hi>work of grace</hi> upon the heart, ſometimes the <hi>holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> is pleaſed to put <hi>Grace</hi> into <hi>freſh actings,</hi> whereby it is more eaſily diſcerned; as for example, when a <hi>Believer</hi> is examining whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath <hi>true Faith in Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> doth ſometimes put that <hi>grace</hi> into act at that very time, and then he can ſay, <hi>Lord I believe, I ſee faith at this very time working in my heart,</hi> and ſo for other <hi>graces;</hi> as <hi>repentance, love to God,</hi> and the like; When it is thus, a <hi>poor believer</hi> goes thorough <hi>the work of ſelf examination,</hi> with great ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and delight, and if it be not always ſo, yet let a <hi>Believer</hi> pray and ſearch into his heart, and wait upon the Lord: If he hide his face, yet wait upon him for a good hour when he will come unto us and comfort us.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>The ſtronger the habit of grace in the heart is, and the more frequent and conſtant the actings of grace are, the more eaſily may we come to the knowledg and aſſurance of the work of grace in us.</hi> If <hi>faith</hi> were ſtronger in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit and more frequent in the act, we might have more aſſurance that we have the <hi>truth</hi> of that <hi>grace,</hi> and uſually it is ſo, that ſuch
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:192261:77"/>have moſt aſſurance, the like may be ſaid of <hi>repentance, love to God,</hi> and other <hi>graces.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Happy is it, when a man can truly ſay, <hi>ſhall I queſtion the truth of my faith in Chriſt, when through the grace of God who hath wrought my heart to this ſelf ſame thing, I find a ſtrong bent upon my heart to cleave to Chriſt as my Mediatour for ever. I am continually looking to him he is precious to me the Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him is ſweet to my ſoul, I have counted, do count, and will for ever count, all things but dung in compariſon of him, ſhall I queſtion the truth of my repentance, when I find that I have continual ſorrow in my heart for my ſins and ſighs, and cry continually to be delivered from all my corruptions.</hi> I ſay happy is that man whoſe grace is ſo ſtrong and in ſuch conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual motion and action ſuch a man can more eaſily diſcern the truth of it let us pray and wait for this.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Believers muſt not be taken up wholly in trying of themſelves whether they are in the ſtate of grace or no; but preſs forwards in putting forth New acts of Faith, New acts of repentance, New acts of love to Chriſt, and New acts of mortification of Sin.</hi> That we may grow up into him in all grace, who is our head even Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:192261:78"/>
               <p>Yea, ſometimes former <hi>grace</hi> received may be many ways ſo obſcured, yea weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that there is no other way to recover the vigour and comfort of <hi>grace,</hi> but for the Soul to believe in Chriſt; repent and turn to God as if it were but now to begin to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Converſion and the work of grace upon the heart, is ſometimes manifeſted to us by the more immediate teſtimony of the ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the holy Ghoſt do indeed perſwade and aſſure our hearts that we are in the love and favour of God, then we are effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for though God loveth thoſe whom he hath choſen from everlaſting, and the giving of Chriſt to die for them, and his drawing them to Chriſt is from that free love and good pleaſure of his will towards them, yet until a perſon be converted the holy Ghoſt doth not aſſure him, that God hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to eternal life. Thoſe whom God hath foreknown, he hath predeſtinated from eternity to the adoption of Children by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, but till they be actually ſons and daughters which is not till their converſion and believing in Chriſt, <hi>John.</hi> 1.12. <hi>The Lord doth not ſend his ſpirit into their hearts to enable them to cry Abba Father.</hi> The Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſendeth his ſpirit into the hearts of the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:192261:78"/>Elect to convert them and work faith in them (for without the ſpirit it could never be done) but it is an after work for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to come into our hearts enabling us to cry, <hi>Abba Father;</hi> aſſuring us that we are the Children of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. And ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abroad and pouring in the love of God to us in particular into our hearts <hi>Rom.</hi> 5 5.</p>
               <p>We muſt not think, that the holy Ghoſt at firſt daſh doth aſſure a perſon that God hath ordained him in particular to eternal life, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he inſufe the habit of grace and ſpiritual Life into him, but firſt the holy Ghoſt having convinced the ſoul of ſin, and convinced the Soul of righteouſneſs to juſtify, to be in Chriſt, and in him alone doth enable the ſoul to apply Chriſt, and come unto him, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards as it pleaſes him doth manifeſt to the ſoul the truth of his faith, and his pardon through Chriſt. The Holy Ghoſt works as a Sanctifyer, before he workes as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, the Holy Ghoſt workes faith in the heart before he fill with joy and peace, which is onely in believing in Chriſt; and diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fruits of our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with him.</p>
               <p>The manner how the Holy Ghoſt doth aſſure us that we are the Children of God, is a great myſtery. When the Holy Ghoſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:192261:79"/>clears to us the work of grace upon our hearts, this is one way that he doth witneſs to us that we are the Children of God. But ſometimes he doth it more immediately, that when the believer hath not been at that time trying his ſpiritual eſtate, or it may be is in great heavineſs through manifold inward temptations, and outward dangers, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions; ſuddenly the Holy Ghoſt makes him to triumph in Chriſt and rejoyce with joy unſpeakable and full of glory. Indeed this way of the ſpirits witneſſing to the ſoul, though it is moſt refreſhing and raviſhing, yet it is not ſo ordinary as the other, and it is more tranſient and quickly paſſing away: and is rather a cordial for ſome ſowning fit or ſome <hi>Antidote</hi> to ſtrengthen the heart in ſome great appraoching ſervice or tryal then the common food of the Saints in this life.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall ſay, <hi>how do Believers know the voice and witneſs of the ſpirit ſpeaking peace, and joy, by Jeſus Chriſt to their ſouls from a deluſion,</hi> I anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>By a certain ſpiritual inſtinct which no man knows but him that hath it;</hi> by this they know the voice of the ſpirit from the voice of a ſtranger.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>By the ſigns that follow this voice and
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:192261:79"/>Witneſs of the ſpirit raiſing our hearts to look to Chriſt the Mediatour.</hi> As he from whom all our ſprings are admiring the love of the father in giving him to be the propitiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for our ſins; loathing of our ſelves for our iniquities and ſtronger deſires to walk in univerſal obedience to the Lord.</p>
               <p>But now becauſe ſome ſeem to examine themſelves little concerning the work of grace upon their hearts, but in giving a reaſon of the hope they have, that they are paſſed from death to life, ſpeak not of their faith, repentance and other graces: but ſay that they had ſuch and ſuch a word, given in as for example I have loved thee with an everlaſting love, or I have blotted out as a thick Cloud thy tranſgreſſions, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy ſins no more; <hi>Fear not I am with thee, be not diſmayed, for I am thy God be of good cheare, thy ſins are forgiven thee or the like.</hi> This queſtion may be moved hereupon.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>When a man hath ſome promiſe or word of grace come into his thoughts ſo as to make impreſſion upon his heart, and quiet him as to his feare of the wrath of God: how ſhall he know that this is ſpoken by the ſpirit to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to him, that he is the Child of God or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be a deluſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:192261:80"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 That the holy Ghoſt doth ſometimes comfort the hearts of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, by ſome promiſe or word of grace mentioned in the Scripture is not to be queſtioned.</p>
               <p>As the Holy Ghoſt in convincing men of ſin and their laſt eſtate by nature doth often make uſe of ſome places of Scripture, as for example the wages of ſin is death, the wrath of God is revealed from heaven againſt all unrighteouſneſs of men, and ſetles home the commandments of the Law with the curſe anexed to the breach of them in particular to the ſoul, as if the Lord did ſpeak from heaven, to that particular perſon, <hi>I have ſaid in my Law; thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me? But thou haſt made riches thy God, thy belly, thy God, thy Name and eſteem amongſt men thy God; therefore thou art cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: I have ſaid in my Law thou ſhalt not take my Name in vain but thou hast done it, I have ſaid thou ſhalt keep my ſabbath Holy, but thou haſt not regarded it; and ſo thou haſt broaken this commandment, and the other, I have ſaid curſed is every one that continueth not in every thing, that is written in the book of the Law, to do it therefore thou art under the curſe: and what wilt thou do. As the holy Ghoſt, I ſay doth often ſet home ſuch Scriptures
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:192261:80"/>to convince men oſ ſin, and ſhew them their need of Chriſt, ſo doth the Holy Ghoſt many times make uſe of other Scriptures that hold forth Gods free grace in Chriſt; both at firſt to work faith and draw the ſoul to Chriſt, and afterwards to fill the heart with joy and peace in believing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thefore it is a ſign of a prophane heart, and deſtitute of the knowledge of converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of the comforts of the holy Ghoſt, to make a mock and jeare of Scriptures, and promiſes given into and ſet home upon the ſpirits of men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sometimes promiſes and words of grace are given into the ſoul to work grace at that time, and not to witneſs that grace was wrought before, for we ordinarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ſpirit to work grace at firſt in us by hearing in the preaching of the word (or elſe darted more immediately from God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſouls) ſome promiſe or declaration of Gods grace in Chriſt, and if that be all our miſtake, that at ſuch a time when we thought the Holy Ghoſt ſet home ſuch or ſuch a promiſe; and word of grace upon our hearts, to aſſure us that we were the Children of God, that he did it at that time to work the firſt ſpecial grace in us, and unite us unto Chriſt; ſo that, that was the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:192261:81"/>time of our firſt receiving Chriſt: If this I ſay be all the miſtake it is not dangerous.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Laſtly it muſt be granted that all that have a promiſe or word of grace, come into their minds yea though it take ſome impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on them and quiet their thoughts and affect them with a kind of joy for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, have not theſe words given in by the ſpirit of God either to work ſaving grace in them at that time, or to bear witneſs to them that they are in the ſtate of grace, for ſuch as are compared in the Scripture to the ſtony ground, do ſometimes hear the word with joy and conſequently have it come into their thoughts, with ſome flaſhes of joy and thoſe that fall away do taſt of the heavenly gift, and after a ſort are made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. In ſome of his common motions, and impreſſions upon their hearts as hath been opened more largely before. ſo that for a concluſion of this matter. If there be not a work of grace wrought in the heart, even an abiding work as well as promiſes &amp; words of grace, that tranſiently and ſuddenly paſs thorough the thoughts we may be fearfully miſtaken about our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual eſtates. But if we can find ſuch faith in Chriſt, ſuch repentance, and ſuch love to God wrought in us as have before been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:192261:81"/>of, the more promiſes and words of grace are caſt into our thoughts the better, for they ſtrengthen true believers in holineſs and communion with God; and are as ſo many love-tokens ſend them from Jeſus Chriſt by the ſpirit, till they come to him in heaven. Hypocrites and notional profeſſours turn ſuch promiſes and words of grace into wantonneſs, and into a ſnare to their own ſouls, but true believers get real good by them, and lay up theſe ſayings in their hearts and cleave the more unto the Lord in faith and holineſs.</p>
               <p>Thus I have endeavoured to ſhew how we may know we are in the ſtate of grace, let me ſpeak a word or two to thoſe that are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and have had it cleared up to their ſouls that it is ſo</p>
               <p n="10">10. Praiſe the Lord for the exceeding riches of his grace. Be content yea rejoyce and be thankful whatever ſad loſs of outward trouble and affliction lye upon you, grace hath abounded towards you, the Lord hath not dealt ſo with many others as he hath dealt with you, look round about you and ſee what multitudes lye in wickedneſs in groſſe ignorance and prophaneſs, and live without God in the world, what if you be poor in the World; you are heirs of Gods
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:192261:82"/>Kingdom what if you have not health of body as others have, you ſhall ſoone leave this ruinous earthly Tabernacle; and be with Chriſt in Paradiſe, and he will alſo raiſe up this poor frail body, and make it like to his glorious body, at the laſt day what if near relations Father and Mother ſhould forſake you, the Lord hath taken you up into his everlaſting Armes where he will hold you for ever, what though the world hate you, and curſe you, the eternal God hath loved you and bleſſed you in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Rejoycing in the Lord and praiſing him cont inually, are comely for thoſe that are converted and pardoned in Chriſt? <hi>O ſing and give Praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 After God hath once given you a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable aſſurance of your converſion, do not call all in queſtion upon every fit of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and darkneſs, that comes upon your Spirits. Be humbled for the leaſt ſin, but ſay not upon every ſpiritual fall that if there had been truth of grace; you had never done thus, for after converſion there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in this life fleſh and corruption, that is not wholy taken away, till death. Then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the houſe of the Old Man will quite fall, and all theſe Philiſtines die with us.
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:192261:82"/>This makes poor Believers with <hi>Sampſon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to die that all their luſts may die too.</p>
               <p>Neither do you call all into queſtion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of outward afflictions, how great and many ſo ever they are, <hi>for whom the Lord loveth, he chaſtneth, and correcteth every ſon whom he receiveth.</hi> But ſay in your hearts the Lord hath humbled us for our ſins, drawn us to Chriſt, put his fear into our hearts; and hath given us many times gracious hints of his favour to us in Chriſt, and now though he ſeem to walk contrary to us in ſome outward diſpenſations, and breaks us in our relations, and breaks us in our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and breaks us in our eſteem, and breaks us in our-health (as it was thus with <hi>Jacob</hi>) yet will we truſt in him; and ſay that ſtill he is our Father, and will not alwaies chide nor retain his anger for ever.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let thoſe that are converted, hate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very falſe way, and meddle with ſin no more we may well ſay the time paſt ſuffices, and yet we have had to much of ſinning already. The ſtate of grace is ſo far from giving any liberty to ſin, that it layes more obligation to holineſs, have a care of the ſins of the daies wherein we live, worldlineſs, miſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of time in unprofitable talk, bitterneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that differ never ſo little from
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:192261:83"/>us in judgment neglect of training up Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the fear of God, and reverence and ſubjection to their parents, want of heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcourſe, pride in apparel, falſe and long haire; and abundance of other ſins that are to rife amongſt ſome that make a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Shew forth the Praiſes of him that hath called you out of darkneſs into his marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous light, ſhew forth his praiſes not only in words, but in works, glorifie him on the earth; let not his high and holy Name be blaſphemed through you. Be exceeding tender of the Name and glory of God: make not Religion to ſtink, and the ſavour of it to be abhorred by your covetous practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, proud carriage, looſe converſation, adorn the profeſſion of religion with a ſerious chearfulneſs, a meak zeal, a heavenly dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in your callings, and with a loving and yet a convincing converſation to the World; theſe things may well go together and ſhould do ſo. Chriſtians ſhould be ſerious and yet chearful, they have moſt cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce: and ſhall do it when others ſhall weep and howl; and gnaſh their teeth. Chriſtians ſhould be meek, peaceable, gentle, eaſiy to be entreated and yet zealous magnanimous and valiant for the truth. Chriſtians ſhould
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:192261:83"/>be heavenly in their thoughts and affections and diſcourſe, and yet deligent in their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward callings, heavenly mindedneſs makes the yoak of outward labour eaſier, and the burden of it lighter. Chriſtians ſhould be affable, courteous, loving to all, yet ſo far from ſinful compliance with the waies of the world, that they ſhould hold forth the grace of Chriſt, in their converſations that others may be convinced that they are the Children of God, and that though poſſibly they may rail at them with their mouths, they may ſecretly commend them in their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and wiſh their death at laſt end might be like theirs.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:192261:84"/>
            <head>A concluding Speech to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCONVERTED.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Containing advice and counſel to thoſe who are yet unconverted.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving ſhewn the neceſſity of converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Nature and ſigns of it, I ſhall now conclude with ſome advice and council to thoſe who are ſtrangers to any work of grace upon their hearts, but are going on in ignorance and blindneſs and ſee not into what a gulph and bottomleſs pit of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are going.</p>
               <p>Wonder not that I am earneſt in ſuch a matter, and tell you ſo much of Hell and damnation, it is to ſtop them that being ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually blind and deſparate, are running in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lake of fire and brimſton, which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for ever. Well then let me direct my ſpeech unto ſuch, if God peradventure will give them repentance that ſo they may be
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:192261:84"/>recovered out of the ſnare of the Devil, and eſcape everlaſting deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Hearken and give ear to this Alarm that is now ſounded to you that are yet ignorant, and careleſs of the things that belong unto your everlaſting peace, Repent, repent, get into Chriſt, the City of refuge quickly, quickly before the Lord come forth againſt you in his wrath and fury, and you be caſt into Hell. I ſhall endeavour to ſet before you, the miſerable condition, you will be in to eternity, if you die in your ſins and to that end I ſhall ſhew you three things.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The certainty of Hell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>the miſery of Hell.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The eternity of Hell.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Conſider the certainty of Hell.</hi> This is that which I would ſpeak of firſt, That there is a place of torment and extream miſery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which the wicked are caſt, their ſouls en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring firſt into this woful place as ſoon as they depart this life; and at the Day of Judgment their bodies being raiſed by the Almighty power of God ſhall be united a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with their ſouls, that ſo both in body and ſoul, they may bear the wrath of God for ever.</p>
               <p>It may be ſome that may read this may be ſo ignorant and prophane that they may
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:192261:85"/>think that Hell is a fable deviſed to keep me in awe, and think them fools that are ſcar'd with it, therefore let me endeavour to convince them of it, for it doth appear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by the lives of too many, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve neither Heaven nor Hell, yet there are ſuch fools that ſay in their hearts, there is no God too, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.1. They ſay ſo in their hearts, and ſay ſo in their lives, though few of them are ſo impudent as to ſay it with their mouths.</p>
               <p>To prove that there is a Hell, I might ſhew that the very heathens as they have a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that there is a God, ſo they have a Nation that there is a Hell; a ſtate and place of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery into which evil men go after this life, likewiſe I might ſhew that the boldeſt Athieſts are ſometimes ſtruck with a Pannick fear of Hell, all which proves that it is an univerſal Notion of mankind, that the ſoul is immortal, and that there is happineſs or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery after this life though Atheiſts ſmother this conviction what they can. But I ſhall onely inſiſt upon Scripture proof of this point.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The wicked ſhall be turned into Hell,</hi> Pſal. 9.18. <hi>How can ye eſcape the damnation of Hell,</hi> Mat. 23.33 <hi>Fear him that is able to deſtroy Soul and body in Hell,</hi> Mat. 10.28.
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:192261:85"/>
                  <hi>God ſpeared not the Angels that ſinned but thruſt them down to Hell,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.4.</p>
               <p>To name no more particular places; when ye read in the Scripture of everlaſting puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the wrath to come, unquenchable fire, all thoſe expreſſions, point at the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>As there is a real Hell, as well as there is a real Heaven, ſo there is a local Hell, as well as there is a local Heaven. Hell and Heaven are not expreſſions, onely to ſet forth the two ſtates and conditions of men after this life, but the two places, to one of which all go at death.</p>
               <p>Let none out of curoſity enquire where Hell is, 'tis-ſufficient that the Scripture tells us that there is a Hell, and tells us what will bring us thither that we may avoid it and that Chriſt onely can deliver us from it that we may make ſure of our intereſt in him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Conſider the miſery of Hell.</hi> Though there be a Hell, yet if it were a tollerable good place and condition though far inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to Heaven it was not to be ſo much feared but O let us conſider the miſery of Hell.</p>
               <p>I might inſiſt upon that which is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the puniſhment of loſs that is what
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:192261:86"/>the damned are deprived of, and what ſad reflections they may make upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, being not onely deprived of all the creature comforts which once they enjoyed in this world (which the Saints in Heaven cannot reflect upon as any loſs to them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is there all in all, and better then all to them) but they are ſeperated from God, from any hope of his favour and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of him ſhut out of the place where he ſhews the riches of his glorious Kingdom and the honour of his excellent majeſty to the Angels and Saints, not for a time onely but for ever. Shut out of the company of the Holy Angels and Saints. Surely theſe things gall the ſpirits of the damned. If <hi>Eſau</hi> wept ſo bitterly for that he had loſt the birthright, and loſt an earthly Fathers bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing how bitterly may the damned weep that they have loſt Heaven, and the bleſſing of the Father of Spirits? What better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections the damned make upon their fall in <hi>Adam</hi> (which now ſo little affects the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of men) and their great loſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we cannot conceive now, nor how it will vex and fret them to think (ſome of them) what means of grace they enjoyed in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werful preaching of the Word, and good council of Parents, Maſters, and Friends
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:192261:86"/>but that they have loſt all thoſe advantages for Heaven which once they had, and made light of.</p>
               <p>But let me ſpeak ſomething of that poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive miſery or puniſhment of ſenſe, that the damned undergo.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They are miſerable for their place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They are miſerable for their company.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>They are miſerable for the wrath of God which They beare, this is the worſt of all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>They are miſerable for their place.</hi> I ſhall not ſtand much upon this but ſurely Hell is a doleful place, therefore compared to Tophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.33. <hi>To a bottomleſs pit,</hi> Rev. 9.2. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tter darkneſs,</hi> Mat. 22.13.</p>
               <p>Heaven is called Paradiſe, <hi>Luke.</hi> 23.43. <hi>Hell a Priſon,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.19. But I but touch this for the truth is as the enjoyment of God in Heaven, is the Heaven of Heaven, the beſt of Heaven, and not meerely the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour and glory of the place (though it is a glorious place) ſo it is the bearing of the wrath of God in Hell, that is the Hell of Hell, the worſt of Hell, though it is alſo a doleful and miſerable place.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>They are miſerable for their company.</hi> Now men are fit to go out of their wits if the Devil appear to them, what will they do, how will they be eternally ſcared and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>igt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:192261:87"/>when they know they are amongſt a throng of them ſhut up with them in the ſame eternal Priſon.</p>
               <p>That Devils and damned Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall he together in the ſame place of torment, is cleare from the ſentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, at the laſt day, <hi>depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels,</hi> Mat. 25.41.</p>
               <p>As thoſe of the Children of men that are ſaved ſhall be in the ſame Heaven with the elect Angels, and their company will be a great refreſh ng to them, ſo thoſe that are damned ſhall be in the ſame Hell, with the faln Angels, the Devils and their company will be a great terrour to them.</p>
               <p>And as much as prophane men delight in in one anothers company, now it will be very grievous to them in Hell. To hear one anothers, howlings, weeping, wayling, groanings, and bitter Lamantatioas will ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be very terrible, and eſpecially the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of thoſe that have been partners in ſin, fellow-drunkards, fellow-thiefs, fellow-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors, fellow-wantons, will be very grievous. O how they will curſe one another and courſe the days that ever they ſaw one another.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>They are miſerable for the wrath of God
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:192261:87"/>that abideth on them.</hi> It is not meerly the place nor the company that makes them mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, but the ſting of Hell is the mediate ſenſe and feeling of the wrath of God in an unſportable manner, this is their paenal Hell, which is worſe than their local Hell.</p>
               <p>As God lets out his love and makes great impreſſions thereof upon the ſpirits of the Saints in Heaven, ſo he lets out his wrath and makes great impreſſions thereof upon the damned in Hell.</p>
               <p>The damned are ſaid in the Scripture to be <hi>puniſhed, tormented, beaten with ſtripes, burnt with unquenchable fire,</hi> all to ſhew how the wrath of God lies very hard upon them.</p>
               <p>It is true there are degrees of torments in Hell, more and fewer ſtripes a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, there is no doubt of the ſufferings of the damned, ſome receive greater damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and beare more wrath then others, 'tis according as men have ſinned more or leſs in this world (I ſpeak of thoſe that periſh) that they are punniſhed more or leſs in Hell. But ſurely thoſe that have feweſt ſtripes, and the cooleſt places in Hell, have a ſad portion.</p>
               <p>If people do verily believe that there is a Hell, yet few believe the extremity of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:192261:88"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:192261:88"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:192261:89"/>that is ſuffered there.</p>
               <p>I remembre a poor Woman that ſuffered death for being a Witch, told me, that after ſhe had made a contract with the Devil, ſhe began to be much afraid of Hell, as a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable place and condition, whereupon the Devil told her that Hell was not ſo bad a place as people thought, that he was the prince of the aire that people lived very well in his dominions, and that ſhe for her part ſhould be an hoſteſs and keep a fair Inn there. It was to this purpoſe what this poor ignorant Woman told me. The Devil hath ſcarce the face to tell his followers that there is no Hell but rather that it is a tollerable good place and not bad as ſome zealous preachers would make them believe.</p>
               <p>At another time I heard a prophane man when he was told of Hell fire ſay, I hope there are ſome ponds of cold water there to where I may go and cole my ſelf when I am heated and ſcorched with the flames, thus fools now make a mock of ſin and a mock of Hell too, till they came to it and then they will be paſt their jeſting. Hell torments put the greateſt wits, and the moſt ſanguine tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers paſt their Joaks and meriment. Many go laughing and merry to Hell but when they come once there, they laugh no more
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:192261:89"/>for there is nothing but weeping, and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and gnaſhing of teeth in Hell.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Conſider the eternity of Hell.</hi> Though there be ſuch miſery in Hell, yet if men were to be there but a little while, it were not ſo much to be feared, but none that go thither return again, neither take they hold of the paths of Life. Therefore 'tis ſaid in the Scripture, that the wicked go into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting puniſhment as the righteous go into life eternal <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.46. <hi>They ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with everlaſting deſtruction,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9. <hi>Their Worme dieth not, and the fire is not quenched</hi> Mark. 9.44.</p>
               <p>It is true, that neither utter deſpaire nor eternity of ſuffering are of the eſſence of the puniſhment due to ſin, for if men could ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy the juſtice of God for the debt of ſin, there were no cauſe of diſpare, neither would they be deteined for ever under the wrath of God, but the damned being never able to make fatisfaction for their ſins, it doth unavoidably follow that they are ſwallowed up of diſpare, and that the wrath of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth on them for ever.</p>
               <p>Now let thoſe who go on deſperately in their ignorance and prophaneſs, conſider theſe things before it be to late, before the decree hath brought forth before the gulph
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:192261:90"/>is fixed, and the day of grace be over.</p>
               <p>God hath made a Hell for the glory of his Juſtice to ſhine in, and all impenitent and unbelieving ſinners ſhall be as fuel for his Holy Juſtice to burn upon for ever. Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, tremble, weep, and howl, all ye that are going on in the broad way to deſtruction, for the miſeries that ſhall come upon you, except you repent, God ſpared not the Angels that ſinned, God ſpared not the Old World, God ſpared not <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorah,</hi> multitudes, multitudes are already in Hell, for the ſame ſins that you are guilty of, and if you do not now ſeek the Lord and make peace with him in Chriſt; ſhall you eſcape?</p>
               <p>It is time, high time to ſeek the Lord, to make ſupplication to your judge, through the Advocate for ſinners, Jeſus Chriſt before all this miſery come upon you.</p>
               <p>But may ſome ſay we do not love to hear ſo much of Hell and damnation, it is a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to us.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, did not Chriſt in his doctrine tell the people much of Hell and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.2, 30. <hi>Luke.</hi> 16.19.20.21.22.23. <hi>And thrice in five verſes he uſes that terrible expreſſion to ſet forth the miſery of Hell that their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched,</hi> Mark. 9.44, 45, 46, 47, 48.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:192261:90"/>
                  <hi>Surely Chriſt knew how to preach, and ſurely he is the beſt pattern of preaching, and you ſee he ſpake much of Hell in his doctrine.</hi> Mat. 24.51. Mat. 25.41, 46.</p>
               <p>Indeed moſt people are like thoſe of old, who ſaid to the ſeers ſee not, and to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets propheſy not, propheſy not unto us right things, propheſy unto us ſmooth things <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.16. As if men ſhould ſay let us go on quietly to Hell, I pray do not trouble our conſciencies, we will venture our Souls, and if we do come to Hell at laſt we muſt bear it as well as we can. I but if the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to make you his people, he will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to go on in ſuch a deſperate way, but he will make you willing to hear of your danger, and make you to enquire in good earneſt how you may eſcape it, yea you ſhall bleſs the Lord that ever you came to ſee into what a gulph and bottomleſs pit you were falling, that ſo you might ſeek for help and ſalvation in Chriſt the Mediatour.</p>
               <p>All that hath been ſaid to ſhew men the certainty, the miſery, and the eternity, of Hell is that they may avoid it, and may never come into that place of torment. And let all know that though the Doctrine of Hell is to be urged unto men, to awaken them, yet Miniſters are not to ſtop there, but to hold
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:192261:91"/>forth Chriſt as an object of faith to them that they may look to him and be ſaved. The ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of the Law are not to be preached ſimply for themſelves, as it were to torment men before the time, but for another end to ſhew them their need of Chriſt, and that they may prize him and beleive on him to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life; Miniſters cannot ſpeak to much of Hell, if withal they held forth Chriſt as he that delivereth from that wrath to come. The hearing of Hell is uſeful, even to thoſe that are in Chriſt that they may be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually prayſing God that hath delievered them from going down to that pit: whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever afflictions and chaſtnings they have here.</p>
               <p>He that only tells people of Hell and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is a meer legal preacher but he that ſhews men firſt their miſerable and loſt eſtate in themſelves, and then holds forth Chriſt to them as a Saviour and ranſom for their ſouls is the right Goſpel preacher.</p>
               <p>As I have ſpoken of the judgment, and fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry indignation of God that ſhall conſume thoſe that die in their ſins ſo let me ſhew how we may be delivered from this wrath to come, and ſo make an end.</p>
               <p>The Goſpel taken in a ſtrict ſenſe is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the good news and glad tidings (glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:192261:91"/>indeed) of a Saviour for loſt ſinners. A wonderfull thing indeed is the Goſpel, it holdeth forth ſuch a way of juſtifying ſinners as could never have entred into the heart of Man to conceive, <hi>if the Lord had not reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. It ſhews us wonder upon wonder, God was manifeſt in the fleſh, that is one great miſtery and wonder of the Goſpel what a condeſcention and humbling of himſelf was this. That Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt took upon him our Nature, our fleſh, not in appearance but really, not to lay it down ſoon again, but <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting it to his God-head for ever,</hi> to be ſure it was to do a great work, that <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Men ſhall admire to eternity, that God was manifeſt in the fleſh.</hi> This is ſuch a wonder that when it is deeply weighed doth overſet the Spirit of Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This mighty one the Son of God, not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint but willingly died for ſinners, had our iniquities laid upon him,</hi> Iſa. 53.6. Bare the puniſhment of them, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>This was the cauſe of his bitter paſſion of all his inward end outward ſufferings. The Jews crucified him as if he had been an evil doer but Chriſt knew what was the Fathers meaning, and his own</hi> (viz) that he ſhould ſuffer and be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied becauſe they, in whoſe ſtead he ſuffered, were realy evil doers, ſinners, and had deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved all that he underwent for them. <hi>Thus he
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:192261:92"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="161" facs="tcp:192261:92"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="162" facs="tcp:192261:93"/>that was perfectly just ſuffered in the room of the unjuſt, A ſurety paid the great debt that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had contracted;</hi> There is a wonderful myſtery in the death of Chriſt, <hi>He died as the Second Adam, as a mediatour, as a publick perſon for his people, for this cauſe he came into the World, for this cauſe he laid down his life, elſe theſe things had never been.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Jeſus, God man, mighty, to ſuffer, bare that puniſhment due to our ſins; which if it had been laid upon us would have been eternal, but he overwraſtled it, made ſatisfaction, put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf, made peace and obtained eternal redemption for us whereof he hath given aſſurance unto all men, in that after he had the iniquities of all his people</hi> laid and charged upon him, <hi>yet he roſe again the third day, is gone unto the Father and is ſet down at the right hand of the Majeſty in the Heavens.</hi> By one offering upon the <hi>Croſs</hi> he did the work, <hi>he being an infinite Perſon, God as well as Man, his ſhort ſuffering was of an infinit value. He dieth no more, there is no need at all of it, in referance unto thoſe, for whom he made his ſoul an offering for ſins, he hath done the work fully, to whom be glory for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the Summ and ſubſtance of the Goſpel. <hi>Now if any hearing of the danger they are in of the wrath of God, for their ſins
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:192261:93"/>and ſenſible of the Rebellion and perverſneſs of their hearts and wayes against God, would have a Saviour and a ſanctifier that it may go well with them for ever, this is he,</hi> Jeſus <hi>the Son of God.</hi> He is not here now upon earth to be ſeen with bodily eyes, he is gone into Heaven and is on the right hand of God. <hi>Look up to him there with an eye of Faith, put your truſt in him, he is able to ſave to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt all that come to God by him.</hi> Get the knowledge of him out of the word, <hi>ſearch the Scriptures for they teſtify of him, they tell you what he is, what he hath done, and what he hath ſuffered to bring us to God. Think of him continually, prize him, ſet your hearts on him, if you flight him, you will find there is no other Saviour, no other Mediatour, no other advocate with the Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the work be yet to be done, even now whilſt thou readeſt theſe things look to him, cloſe with him, give up thy ſelf to him to be ſaved and Sanctified by him, fall in love with him, you will never repent of your choice. Poor ſoul, what ſaiſt thou to a Pardon for all thy ſins? what ſaiſt to peace with God? what ſaiſt thou to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life? Come to Chriſt and thou ſhalt have all theſe, and a New Heart and ſpirit to walk in holineſs and obedience before God too. O doth the Lord affect thy heart</hi> (for he
<pb facs="tcp:192261:94"/>doth this great work) <hi>that thou art taken with Chriſt, and art a thirſt for this water of life; then take it freely, as excellent and precious as the</hi> Lord Jeſus <hi>is, he beſtowes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf freely upon poor ſinners;</hi> the beſt quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication you can have for receiving Chriſt is to ſee your need of him; and that you are altogether unworthy of him, do you ſee your ſins now, the multitude of them, the hainouſneſs of them, let not your ſins drive you from Chriſt, but drive you to Chriſt. <hi>Come, poor ſinners, come to Chriſt his blood clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth from all ſin, his righteouſneſs is able to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all your unrighteouſneſs.</hi> Come to Chriſt but with a true Heart, to give him all the glory of your ſalvation, and to deſire now to have him reign over you, and fear not he is mighty to ſave. <hi>Jeſus is the Lord of glory, conſider his God-head in your looking to him to take away your ſins.</hi> Never any Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient came to this Phiſitian and miſſed of cure, come with all the ſpiritual <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers</hi> run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Sores</hi> and Bloody <hi>Iſſues</hi> of ſin, <hi>touch the hem of his Garment by Faith</hi> (as the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the Goſpel did) <hi>and you ſhall ſee there is vertue enough in Chriſt to make you whole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Devil labours to make men confident and preſumptuous, when they are going on gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
<pb facs="tcp:192261:94"/>in ſin, but when they are convinced of their loſt eſtate and are looking after Chriſt, then he endeavours to puzle them with many doubts and ſuſpitions as if they were paſt cure, and it were too late now to lock after Chriſt. Ah poor ſouls do not you ſee that the hand of Sathan is in all this.</hi> When you went on in ignorance and prophaneſs, he would not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure you ſhould hear, when Miniſters prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of damnation, and now that you are convinced and ſtopt in your vile courſes, and are thinking how you may make peace with God, now the Devil cannot endure you ſhould hear of Salvation in Chriſt the Son of God, leaſt you ſhould come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that you may have life.</p>
               <p>Thus I have ſet before them that are not yet converted life and death pardon of ſin, peace with God and eternal life, if the Lord giveth them hearts to repent and cloſe with Chriſt, The Wrath of God and eternal deſtruction; <hi>If they ſtill go on in their ignorance, prophaneſs, and ſlighting of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> If any that read theſe things ſhall ſay in their hearts, they ſhall have peace and ſhall do well enough (whatſoever ſome zealous preachers ſay) though they caſt Gods law behind their backs, and never look after a work of Grace, and converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:192261:95"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:192261:95"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:192261:96"/>upon their ſouls, the anger of the Lord and his Jealouſy ſhall ſmoake againſt thoſe perſons, and burn againſt them for ever. But if they ſhall now tremble at the word of the Lord, and lay hold upon the offer of Chriſt; believing on his name, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unto him; their ſins ſhall be forgiven them, for his names ſake, and they ſhall be the heir of eternal life through him, for though the wages of ſin is death even eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death, yet the gift the free gift of God is life even eternal life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, to whom be glory for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:192261:96"/>
            <head>Books <hi>Printed</hi> for, and Sold by, <hi>Henry Mortlock,</hi> at the <hi>Phaenix</hi> in <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Church-Yard, and at the White Hart in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Saints <hi>Ebenezer</hi> and Pillar of hope in God when they have none left in the Creature. Or the godly-mans Crutch or Staff in times of ſadning diſappointments, ſinking diſcouragements, ſhaking diſſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherein is ſhewed the Tranſcendent Excellency of God, his Peoples help and hope with the unparalell'd hapineſs of the Saints in their confidence in him over-ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancing the Worldlings carnall depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance both as to ſweetneſs and ſafety by <hi>F. Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A word in ſeaſon or 3 great dutys of Chriſtians in the worſt of times, <hi>(viz:)</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding in Chriſt: Thirſting after his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and ſubmiſſion to his providence; to which is added by way of appendix, the advice of ſome Miniſters to their people for the receiving the power and practice of godlineſs in their familys <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The freeneſs of the grace and love of God to believers diſcover'd in reference to, Firſt Their ſervice and ſuffering, Secondly their conſolations, Thirdly their ſalvation
<pb facs="tcp:192261:97"/>and eternal glory together with the Exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the fear of God.</p>
            <p>The goodneſs and pleaſantneſs of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Love, the wiſdom of hearing the voice of the Rod, repentance the only way to prevent Judgments, delivered in ſeveral Sermons by <hi>William Bridg</hi> ſometimes Preacher of the Word at <hi>Yarmouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Death unſtung in 8 Sermons, Preached at the Funeral of <hi>Tho. Moſeley</hi> an Apothecary who died <hi>July.</hi> 1669 With a brief Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of his Life and Death; Alſo the manner of Gods dealings with him before and after his Converſion drawn up by his own Hand and Publiſhed by <hi>James Jane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> Oct.</p>
            <p>A Fathers Teſtament Written long ſince for the benefit of the Particular Relations of the Author, <hi>Phineas Fletcher,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Hillgay</hi> in <hi>Norfolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The voice of one crying in a Wilderneſs, or the buſineſs of a Chriſtian, both <hi>Anteceda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> to, <hi>Concomitant</hi> of, and <hi>conſequent</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Sore and heavy <hi>Viſitation;</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in ſeveral Sermons. Firſt Preached to his own Family lying under ſuch <hi>Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and now made publick as a thank of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to the Lord his healer by <hi>S. S.</hi> a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God in the Goſpel of his Son.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
